<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eniaytos terastios Mirabilis annus, or, The year of prodigies and wonders being a faithful and impartial collection of severall signs that have been seen in the heavens, in the earth, and in the waters; together with many remarkable accidents, and judgements befalling divers persons, according as they have been testified by very credible hands: all which have happened within the space of one year last past, and are now made publick for a seasonable warning to the people of these three kingdoms speedily to repent and turn to the Lord, whose hand is lifted up amongst us.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84036</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899301</idno>
  <idno type="VID">152943</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240867993</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3127</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229787</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899301</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99899301e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84036)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152943)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2335:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eniaytos terastios Mirabilis annus, or, The year of prodigies and wonders being a faithful and impartial collection of severall signs that have been seen in the heavens, in the earth, and in the waters; together with many remarkable accidents, and judgements befalling divers persons, according as they have been testified by very credible hands: all which have happened within the space of one year last past, and are now made publick for a seasonable warning to the people of these three kingdoms speedily to repent and turn to the Lord, whose hand is lifted up amongst us.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 24, 33-56, 49-64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First two words of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Text and register continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>In this edition, the fourth line of the title ends "Wonders,"; in another edition, the fourth line ends "Won-" (Wing E3127A).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Omens --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152943:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152943:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152943:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152943:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152943:3"/>
            <p>ΕΝΙΑΥΤΟΣ ΤΕΡΑΣΤΙΟΣ <hi>MIRABILIS ANNƲS,</hi> OR, The year of Prodigies and <hi>Wonders,</hi> being a faithful and impartial Collection of severall signs that have been seen in the Heavens, in the Earth, and in the Waters; together with many remarkable Accidents, and Judgements befalling divers persons, according as they have been te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified by very credible hands: all which have happened within the space of one year last past, and are now made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick for a seasonable warning to the People of these three Kingdoms speedily to repent and turn to the Lord, whose hand is lifted up amongst us.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Isaiah 5.11, 12.</hi>
               </bibl> Woe to them that rise up early in the morning that they may follow strong drink, that continue until night till Wine inflame them, and the Harp and the Viol, the Tabret and the Pipe▪ and Wine are in their feasts, but they regard not the Work of the Lord, neither consider the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his hands,</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Psal. 111.2.</hi>
               </bibl> The works of the Lord are great, sought of all them that have pleasure therein.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Revel. 15.4.</hi>
               </bibl> Who shall not fear thee O Lord, and glorifie the Name, for thou only art Holy, for all Nations shall come and worship before thee, for thy judgements are made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest.</q>
            <q>Omnia haec signa sunt imminentis irae Dei quam necesse est quoquo modo possumus ut &amp; annunciemus &amp; prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicemus &amp; deprecemur, <bibl>
                  <hi>Tertul. ad Scap p.</hi> 80.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Quod signum erit irae Dei impiis, erit signum perfectae Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demptionis filiis Dei, <bibl>
                  <hi>Zanch. de oper. Dei, Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 335.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:152943:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152943:4"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>TThe most <hi>natural</hi> and <hi>frequent</hi> works of <hi>God,</hi> ought to be the daily subjects not only of the serious <hi>consideration</hi> but <hi>admiration</hi> also of every sober Christian; <hi>Eliphaz</hi> in <hi>Job</hi> reckons the ordinary Occurrences of natural causes as the rain,<note place="margin">Job. 5.9.10.</note>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> amongst the <hi>great and unsearchable and marvellous things of God.</hi> For indeed nothing lesse then the admirable, infinite, and trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendent Wisdome, Power, and Majesty of the mighty <hi>Jehovah</hi> is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifested, in the most <hi>common</hi> and <hi>usual</hi> constitutions of nature, the whole World being nothing else but Gods Book in Folio, and every Creature and providence as a several page, in which we may plainly read <hi>his eternal Power and God-head;</hi> or like to <hi>Jacobs</hi> ladder, the top in Heaven and the foot on Earth.<note place="margin">Rom. i. 20:</note>
            </p>
            <p>Yea God many times appears greatest in the smallest things, he is more eminently seen in the activity of the souls of the <hi>Dwarf</hi> and <hi>Ant:</hi> then of the <hi>Gyant</hi> and <hi>Elephant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some of the Ancients have affirmed, that the ordinary productions of nature are more <hi>wonderfull</hi> then those things which do obtain a more formal denomination of <hi>miracles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mirabilior est gran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in terra multiplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio quam illa qum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que panum. <hi>August.</hi> John 6.9.10, 11. Acts 14.17.</note> making the multiplication of a grain of corn in the earth, a greater wonder then the multiplying of the <hi>five loaves</hi> by our Saviour, <hi>wherewith he fed five thousand.</hi> If God then had limited the discoveries of himself to the world in these common wayes and means, he had not <hi>left himself without witnesse,</hi> but all men certainly <hi>without excuse,</hi> whiles in defiance of these <hi>impregnable</hi> proofs and demonstrations of a <hi>Deity,</hi> they do remain wilfully ignorant; and brutishly immerse themselves in the stinking lake of an <hi>Atheistical</hi> and <hi>Diabolical</hi> conversation. But that God might adde to this way of manifesting himself the utmost degree of completment and perfection; and that he might also <hi>ex abundenti</hi> prepare a <hi>sovereign</hi> and <hi>sufficient</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote against desperate Atheism, and Irreligon amongst rational crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, he doth many times beyond, above, yea sometimes contrary to the ordinary course of thinges, <hi>make his wonderful works to be remembered;</hi> he doth indeed set bounds to nature,<note place="margin">Psal. 111.4. Psal. 135, 9. Job 9, 10.</note> and will not suffer it at any time <hi>to overflow its banks,</hi> but he will not limit himself, for <hi>whatsoever the Lord pleases that doth he in heaven and in earth in the Seas, and in the deep pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> he will somtimes <hi>do great things past finding out, yea, &amp; wonders with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out noumber.</hi> Upon this account it is that the <hi>Psalmist</hi> contemplating the wonderful <hi>signs</hi> and <hi>judgments</hi> by which <hi>God</hi> did make way for the compleat deliverance of his people out of <hi>Egyptian</hi> bondage, breaks forth into this triumphant challenge, <hi>who is so great a God as our God? Thou art the God that dost wonders, thou hast declared thy strength amongst the People.</hi> Now it is the scope and design of the ensuing <hi>Narrative</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>present God unto the world in his <hi>high</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd <hi>ominent</hi> capacity as a <hi>won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-working God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psalm. 7, 14.</note> and to that purpose we could not but record and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish some of those <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which by impartial and diligent hands have been faithfully gleaned out of several parts of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and are here put together under their proper heads, according
<pb facs="tcp:152943:5"/>to their respective dat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, whereunto we have also added a few suitable Parallels to some of them, as we have been furnished with them from our most Authentick Historians, and as we had opportunity and leisure to find them out.</p>
            <p>But before we proceed a step further, that we might take away all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of mis-belief (from any that may seek occasion) we do make the same solemn <hi>protestation</hi> which <hi>Lycosthenes</hi> did in the like case,<note place="margin">Licet autem multa in his inveniuntur quae rationem ac fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem hominum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedant; <hi>&amp;c.</hi> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stes tamen mihi erit Deus, qui admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabilis est in operi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s suis, ac ipsa eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am coram eodem conscientia salva qua affirmare possum me nihil confinxisse, sed omnia auz ipse oculis meis aetate nostra vidi, aut ab amicis indubitatae tamen fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei explorare potui. <hi>Lycost. de Prsd. Epist. nuncupat.</hi> Mat. 2.2. Luke 2.8, 9, &amp;c. Dan. 5.8. Dan. 12.10.</note>
               <hi>before God, Angels and Men,</hi> that we have not <hi>feigned</hi> any one of the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars here inserted, nor so much as a <hi>Circumsta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce</hi> relating to any one of them, but have <hi>faithfully</hi> and <hi>impartially</hi> published them as they were communicated to us from <hi>credible Persons,</hi> whose proofs also we scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and weighed to the uttermost, and received ample satisfaction in the validity thereof, before we made them publick, casting away many things which we could not but judge <hi>probable,</hi> because not satisfied in the <hi>certainty</hi> of them; Neither let the <hi>paucity</hi> of the Spectators of many of the particulars be a stumbling stone to any, seeing onely the <hi>Magi,</hi> saw <hi>the Star that led to Christ,</hi> and a few <hi>Shepheards</hi> the <hi>Heavenly Host</hi> which proclaimed the Birth of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and upon the credit of their Testimony both these things are inserted in the sacred story. And now having given (as we hope) a <hi>satisfactory</hi> account in the Premises, we shall go on to tell the <hi>Reader</hi> that the <hi>signes</hi> and <hi>Prodigies</hi> contained in the ensuing Discourse, are in themselves like the <hi>hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing</hi> upon the wall in <hi>Belshazzars</hi> Pallace, which the <hi>South sayers, Astrologers,</hi> and <hi>Chaldeans</hi> could neither understand nor read, but the <hi>Saints</hi> may with Gods <hi>Heifer</hi> come to know his <hi>Riddles. The wise shall understand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The things that are here presented to the Reader are <hi>various,</hi> and <hi>remarkable,</hi> the particulars seen in the Heavens are in number fifty four, those in the Earth twenty three, those in the Waters ten, the Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents and Judgements befalling several persons twenty seven; all these, which have been collected but by a <hi>few hands,</hi> (there being we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded many more which have not come to our knowledge) have happened within the compasse of a <hi>year;</hi> the like we believe a <hi>whole age</hi> hath scarce produced in times past, the Lord therein shewing mercy and compassion to the people of these Nations, that though he hath suffered this year so many <hi>hundreds,</hi> if not <hi>thousands</hi> of our able godly, <hi>preaching Ministers</hi> to be <hi>removed into corners,</hi> yet the defect of their Ministry hath been <hi>eminently</hi> supplied by the <hi>Lords</hi> immediate preaching to us from <hi>Heaven,</hi> in the great and wonderful works of his Providence which <hi>Eusebius</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Gods sermons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euseb. Eccles. Hist. Lib. 3. cap. 8. Numb. 17.10. In <hi>Germany,</hi> as their wickednesse and dehauchery did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease, so did the prodigious &amp; strang supernatural acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents multiply ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly, <hi>Hist. Iron Age</hi> p. 66.</note> which this year come to more then two in a week, according to the foregoing <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if (according to the opinion of Learned Men; such as <hi>Luther, Voetius, Weems,</hi> &amp;c.) Prodigies and signes are <hi>especially</hi> for the sakes of <hi>wicked and ungodly men, Aarons Rod budded for a token against the Rebels.</hi> Then from the vast disproportion of their number this year, to what there were for many years together in the times foregoing, we may easily guesse at the prodigious increase of the most bruitish prophan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; Atheism, Uncleannesse, Murders, Blasphemy, and Superstition that <hi>this single year</hi> hath produced, beyond all the Presidents which former times have acquainted us with. And surely by these hainous
<pb facs="tcp:152943:5"/>and unparallel'd enormities, the <hi>Jealous</hi> God hath been exceedingly Provoked, and by his remarkable and strange signes in the Heavens, the Earth and the Waters, doth in a most dreadful manner Alarm the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly world; they are nor only the <hi>Messengers,</hi> but <hi>Harbingers</hi> also of Divine indignation, to such as are <hi>obstinate</hi> in their wickednesse, <hi>who say in their hearts there is no God,</hi> and lead a life worse than that of the people in the time of <hi>Noah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We shall not dare to be positive in a particular Application of all, or any of the portenta mentioned in the following History, knowing it would relish of too much boldnesse and presumption to peep into the Ark of Divine <hi>secrets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Voetius de signis,</hi> &amp;c. page 90.19. <hi>Voet. de sig.</hi> &amp;c. page 930. <hi>Baldvinus, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cas.</hi> p. 813.</note> We shall in this case subscribe to the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Learned <hi>Voetius,</hi> who accounts it no lesse than a <hi>Nefos</hi> to apply Prodigies to particular persons, <hi>sine extraordinario &amp; peculiari</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which we doe not in the least pretend unto; therefore according to the caution given by the same Author, we shall avoid <hi>Cacoethes illud</hi> as he calls it, and conclude with <hi>Balduin; praestat ergo talia in silentio &amp; spe committere Deo quam deviando temeritatem prodere; It is better in silence and hope, to leave things of this nature to God, than by attempting to prognosticate any thing from them, thereby to betray our own rashnesse.</hi> Onely we shall be hold to hint thus much, that accidents of this kind do portend the futurition or manifestation of some things as yet not existent or not known, which usually carry in them some kind of agreement and assimulation to the Prodigies themselves, as (according to the opinion of some Learned men) <hi>the raining of blood</hi> may signifie much slaughter, <hi>the noise of Guns and the apparition of Armies in the Air,</hi> Wars and Commotion, <hi>great innundations,</hi> popular tumults and insur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, yet still we must know that God is ansearchable in his wayes, and our most <hi>critical</hi> and exact observations, together with our best experiences will not capacitate us <hi>fully</hi> to trace him through the Maze and Labyrinth of his Providencies, his way being as <hi>Solomon</hi> speaks,<note place="margin">Prov. 30.19.</note>
               <hi>Like the way of a ship in the sea.</hi> However, that the following discourse might be the more profitable (so far as the Scriptures with the modest conjectures of the most sober amongst the Learned will warrant us) we shall here briefly insert a few of those <hi>general</hi> things which commonly prove the <hi>issues and events</hi> of such <hi>prodigious apparitions</hi> as the ensuing Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story gives us an account of.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They do usually fore-signifie some remarkable <hi>changes</hi> and <hi>revo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions</hi> which b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing with them very sad <hi>calamities</hi> and <hi>distresses</hi> to the generality of the people, amongst whom they happen;<note place="margin">Luke 21.25. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Anxieras gentium in consilii inopi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Beza.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>our Saviour</hi> himself shews a <hi>necessary</hi> connexion between <hi>signés in the Sun, and in the Moon, and in the Stars and upon the Earth distress of Nations with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity.</hi> Great are the influences which these things have in a natural way upon states and Kingdomes in the World, it being a received Maxim amongst the meer <hi>Naturalists,</hi> that some considerable mutations and concussions are the usual products of them, but certainly their Vertue and operation is far greater, as they are <hi>ordained of God</hi> to portend and signifie the most dreadful and important Revolutions of his Providence. These did our <hi>Saviour himselfe</hi> institute and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point as the certaine signes and immediate Fore-runners of that sore Destruction so often threatned, and at last so severely executed by <hi>Titus Vespasian</hi> upon <hi>Jerusalem.</hi> Great honour is likewise given to
<pb facs="tcp:152943:6"/>them by Christ in that he reckons them amongst the <hi>Portenta</hi> and <hi>Presages</hi> of his second Coming. We shall therefore conclude this with those Instances which the <hi>Reverend</hi> and <hi>Learned</hi> Dr. <hi>Jackson</hi> hath furnished us with,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Iackson</hi> Sermon preached before K. <hi>Cha.</hi> 1. on <hi>Luke</hi> 13.5. page 9.</note>
               <hi>viz.</hi> That Testimony of <hi>Herodotus</hi> (who lived before <hi>Alexander the Great,</hi> but after <hi>Cy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> had taken the City <hi>Babylon</hi>) his words (as they are quoted by the said Author) are these <hi>quoties ingentes sunt eventu ae Calamitates vel civitati, vel Nationi solent Signis praenuncia, riextraordinary calamities whether such as befal cities or peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar Signiories are always fore shewn by some sign or other.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Iackson ibid</hi> p.10.</note> His other instance is that of <hi>Matchiavel,</hi> of whom he saies, that he was a man as free from <hi>Superstition</hi> or vain <hi>Credulity</hi> as any other Writer that hath been borne and bred amongst <hi>Christians;</hi> yet he out of his own Reading and Experience hath made the same induction with <hi>Herodotus,</hi> but some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more full, <hi>ut causa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n facile me confitebor ignorare: itarem ipsam cum ex antiquis tum novis exemplis agnoscere oporter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Marchi disp. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publica lib. 1 cap. 56. page 229.</note>
               <hi>&amp; confiteri omnes magnos motus, quicunque aut urbiant regioni venerunt, vel a conjectoribus vel a revelatione aliquâ Prodigiis, aut coeestibus Signis praedici aut prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciari solere; As I must meeds confesse my selfe ignorant of the cause, so the thing it selfe I cannot but acknowledge it to be true, both from antient and modern examples, that the motions and changes which have at any time hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened either to Cities or Countries, have still been foretold or pre-declared either by some southsayers, or else by some discoveries from the Prodigies or Signs in the Heavens;</hi> And afterwards the same <hi>Matchiavel</hi> affirms, that the several <hi>Changes</hi> which happened in <hi>Italy</hi> in his time,<note place="margin">Ibid page 230. Et ne procul petit's ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplis hoe domon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strare velle videar domesticis uter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A Signis Caeli hujus modi paveint impii <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Voet. de Signis page 227. Dan. 5.22, 23. Dan. 5.3.3. Inconsilio vini. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benezra. Verse 4. Verse 5. Verse 28.</note> were still pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saged by divers remarkable <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Prodigies,</hi> whereof he gives parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular instances in the Chapter before cited.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They do bode very much misery and calamity to the <hi>prophane</hi> and <hi>wicked</hi> part of the World (except a through and seasonable re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and turning to God do Intervene) the <hi>Mene Tekel</hi> on the Wall did signifie evil to <hi>Belshazzar,</hi> who though he knew all that God had done to his <hi>Father, yet humbled not his heart, but lifted up himself against the Lord of heaven,</hi> and by his <hi>presence at least</hi> did keep up and encourage <hi>drunken and debauched meetings,</hi> wherein the <hi>Vessels of the temple</hi> (the spoiles of the Lords people) were <hi>prophaned,</hi> the <hi>High</hi> God <hi>blasphemed, and the Gods of Gold, and Silver, of brase, of Iron, of wood, and of stone were praised</hi> and magnified; and saies the Text in <hi>that same hour came forth fingers of a mans hand, &amp;c.</hi> So that God by a Prodigy doth sharply reprove the debauchery of this King and his concubines, with the rest of his <hi>Associetes,</hi> and thereby also de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares the sudden period and determina ion of his <hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But amongst the <hi>Hellish</hi> rout of prophane and ungodly men, let <hi>es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially</hi> the <hi>Opressors</hi> and <hi>Persecutors of the True Church</hi> look to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, when the hand of the Lord in the strange Signs and Wonders is lifted among them; for <hi>then</hi> let them know assuredly <hi>that the day of their Calamity is at hand, and the things that shall come upon them make hast.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.35.</note> The retale and final overthrow of <hi>Pharoah</hi> and the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> (those cruel Task-Masters and Oppressors of the Israelites) did bear date not long after the <hi>wonderful</hi> and the <hi>Prodigious Signs</hi> which the Lord had shewn in the midst of them; Neither could the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Jews</hi> (<hi>who were both the betrayers and murderers of the Lord of Life and Glory,</hi> and did persecute his <hi>Apostles</hi> and <hi>Disciples from City
<pb facs="tcp:152943:6"/>to City</hi>) escape those sad and dreadful effects of the <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies</hi> which Christ long before foretold and forewarned them by, and were indeed according to our Saviours Predictions, the doleful Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sengers of the approaching ruine both of <hi>themselves,</hi> their <hi>City,</hi> and <hi>Temple:</hi> O that therefore all the enemies of <hi>Sion</hi> (who make it their work to <hi>tread the Holy City under foot</hi>) would betimes before the effects of this years wonders take place against them, truly repent,<note place="margin">Rev. 11.2.</note> and be ashamed of all their enmity against the faithful Servants of the <hi>most high God,</hi> least his wrath break forth <hi>and there be none to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 They do usually Prognosticate very much good to the <hi>Sober</hi> and <hi>Religious</hi> part of the World,<note place="margin">Prodigia beneficia credentibus male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fica &amp; horrifica in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credulis. Corn. A. Lap. Com. In Joel 2.30. Psal. 78.52.53.</note> that which severely threatens the ruine and destruction of others, doth clearly portend the security and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of their interest.</p>
            <p>Those signal predictions of <hi>Pharoahs</hi> and the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> overthrow did yet assure the <hi>Israelites</hi> of <hi>their</hi> speedy deliverance, and departure <hi>out of the house of bondage;</hi> therefore when the Psalmists had large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly discoursed of those <hi>Signs</hi> which God did shew in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes with these words, <hi>he made his own people to go forth like Sheep, and guided them in the wilderness like a flock and he led them on safely so that they feared not, but the Sea over-whelmed their enemies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 3.2.7. Sam. 2.22 Chap. Verse 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15.</note> yea the very first discovery that ever the Lord made of saving that <hi>People,</hi> was by the <hi>Prodige</hi> of a burning bush. <hi>David</hi> also speaking of great <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes,</hi> sad and dark <hi>Eclypes,</hi> terrible <hi>Storms,</hi> strange <hi>Fiery Meteors</hi> in the heavens, dreadful <hi>Thunders</hi> and <hi>Lightnings, &amp;c.</hi> Make the end of all this to be nothing else but his own <hi>Deliverance;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verse 17, 18.</note> Therefore he sayes in the close of all, <hi>he sent from above, he took me, he drew me out of many waters, he delivered me from my strong Enemy, and from them that hated me, for they were too strong for me.</hi> The greatest blessing likewise that ever the Church received,<note place="margin">Mat. 2.2.</note>
               <hi>viz.</hi> (the birth of our Lord Jesus Christ (who came into the world on purpose <hi>to save his people from their sins</hi>) was ushered in with the appearance of a strange and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>usual <hi>Star</hi> in the <hi>East,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Est quoque alia ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerabilior &amp; sanctior Historic. quae perhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet oreu stellae cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jusdam insolitae non mosbos moresque prenunciatos, sed descensum Dei ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerabilis ad humanae servationis reremque mortaliem gratiam. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Vid. Dr. Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond In Mat. 2.2. Chap.</note> whereof <hi>Chaelcidius</hi> in his Comment upon <hi>Plato's Timaeus</hi> takes great notice because it signified the coming down of a <hi>God</hi> in favour to the Salvation of men, as Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> hath well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served in his Commention <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.2. Those very <hi>Signs</hi> also which according to <hi>Christs</hi> prophesie did point at the miserable <hi>Desolation</hi> of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> did not withstanding presage the giving of the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> to the <hi>Apostles,</hi> and the first <hi>Gospel Church,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> himselfe affirms in his <hi>Apology</hi> for the <hi>Disciples.</hi> And indeed these strange <hi>Prodigies</hi> were long before by the Prophet <hi>Joel</hi> prophesied of, as the <hi>Harbingers</hi> of that new and Spiritual dispensation under the Gospel according to his <hi>excellent connection I will powr out my spirit upon all flesh, And I will shew wonders in the Heavens. &amp;c.</hi> Which <hi>Peter</hi> in the forementioned <hi>Scripture</hi> makes to be fulfiled in that <hi>wonderful</hi> effusion of the <hi>Spirit</hi> on the day of <hi>Penticost.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea further, our <hi>Lord Jesus Christ himselfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 2.14, 15, 16. Joel 2.28, 29, 30. Mat. 24.30. Luke 21.28.</note> when he speaks of the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>Signs</hi> that shall precede his <hi>second coming,</hi> (at the sight where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>all the trees of the Earth shall mourn</hi>) yet encourages <hi>his people to lift up their hands with joy, because their Redemption draweth nigh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon which words <hi>Luther</hi> thus descants, <hi>behold sayes he this notable
<pb facs="tcp:152943:7"/>Instructer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luthers 1 Serm. on Luke 21.25, 26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> page 27. There is also a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Sermon of Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers on the same Text, now lately translated and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished, in which he much encourages the Godly. To hope and rejoyce in the Lord, when his signs and wonders do appear, that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon is well worth the Reading. Verse. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 30. Sermon ibid page 66.67.</note>
               <hi>who knoweth bette▪ how to expound Signes and Tokens to come than any Southsayer or Astrologer, they only prognosticate terrible and horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble events thereof, but he (unto whom nothing is unknown,) doth foretell them to be tokens of all goodnesse to his people;</hi> And again in the same <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> he observes that the happy and comfortable issues of those <hi>Signs</hi> to the <hi>Godly,</hi> our <hi>Saviour</hi> doth plainly interpret by the <hi>Parable</hi> and <hi>Simi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude</hi> which he makes use of to that purpose. <q>Behold sayes he the fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, and all the Trees when they now shoot forth, ye see and know of your own selves that Summer is now nigh and hand, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Doubtless <hi>sayes Luther on these words,</hi> this is a notable exposition which I my self could never invent, nor apply to this purpose, for who ever heard that the darkning of the Sun and Moon, the destruction of the Heaven and Earth, should be likened to the shooting out of huds, and the blossom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of trees; I would think rather that these things should be likened to a rough, sharp, and very hard Winter, which with intolerable cold destroyeth and killeth all Fruits, and whatsoever groweth upon the Earth. But our Saviour Christ (of all others the best interpreter and expounder of his Word) expoundeth these Signs after another sort, better to our comfort and Consolation; So that now if we see the Sun and the Moon darkened, the Water and the Winds stormy and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pestuous, he teaches us then to say thanks be to God, for now the pleasant summer is at hand, now we see the spring of the leaf in some trees, and other some to shoot out their buds, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> Upon this consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration therefore let all the Lords faithful people observe the Prophets Counsel,<note place="margin">Jer. 10. 2 A signis Coelorum ne consternemini, Iun. Psal. 92.4. Psal. 75.1. Ad liberandum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocantem. <hi>Aben Ezra.</hi> Joel 2.31, 32.</note>
               <hi>not to be dismayed at the signes of Heaven;</hi> But rather with the Psalmist let us <hi>Triumph in the works of Gods hands,</hi> and abound in Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving and Rejoycing, for <hi>that his name is near his wondrous works de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us comfort our selves with this, that where God doth threaten <hi>that the Sun shall be turned into darknesse, and the Moon into blood, &amp;c.</hi> In the very next verse he is pleased to make a gracious promise, <hi>That who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever shall call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved; for in Mount Zion, and in Jerusalem shall be deliverance as the Lord hath said, and in the remnant whom the Lord shall call.</hi> But we shall no longer detaine the <hi>Reader</hi> from the sight and perusal of the ensuing <hi>Collection,</hi> which we desire to accompany with our prayers, that all who read it may lay to heart the things contained in it,<note place="margin">Psalm 28.5.</note> and take heed they <hi>despise not the works of the Lord, not the operation of his hands,</hi> least according to his threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>he destroy them and not build them up,</hi> but let every one rather from these things be convinced, that upon us the ends of the world are come, and that God is now making hast <hi>to consummate</hi> his <hi>whole</hi> work in the earth, and to prepare the way for his <hi>Son to take unto himself his great power and reign;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.13.</note> All these prodigies being according to our Saviours own prediction, but praeludiums to that signal and last revolution which makes way for <hi>the now Heavens and the new Earth, wherein dwels Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse,<note place="margin">Verse 14.</note> And if we look for such things let us be diligent that we may be found of him in Peace, without spot, and blamelesse.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>July 25. 1661.</date>
               </dateline> Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152943:7"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Severall Prodigies and Apparitions seen in the Heavens from <hi>August</hi> the <hi>1. 1660.</hi> to the latter end of <hi>May, 1661.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Two suns seen near</hi> Hertford Aug. <hi>1. 1660.</hi> Naturaliter portendunt &amp; praenuciant Pluvias. <hi>Zanch</hi> de operibus dei, p. <hi>348.</hi> Parheli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us est magnum pluviarum sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. <hi>Her. Tris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meg.</hi> l. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>473</hi> Ex dei autem ordinatione va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae ejus Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia, vel Bella, vel Fames, <hi>&amp;c. Zanch.</hi> ibid. <hi>Pucerus,</hi> lib. Metorolog. p. <hi>340.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Everal persons who were reaping Wheat in a Field about a quarter of a Mile from <hi>Hertford,</hi> near six of the Clock in the Evening, <hi>August</hi> 1. 1660. espyed two Suns in the Firmament, the One West, the Other more Northerly at some distance each from other; they were as they judged of equal height and bignesse, and beams did issue from both, only that more Northerly shone not so bright as the other. They continued in their view near half an hour, and then were both overshadowed by a Cloud. This is Testifyed by honest credible persons who were eye-witnesses.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>These</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>as the Greeks call them, do naturally portend much moysture and rainy weather.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But God ordains them (as some learned men conceive) to sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie several Judgements, as War, Famine, and Pestilence. Some do affirm, they portend the</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">As it happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Anno</hi> 1156. 2 Suns appeard prognostica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the death of <hi>Tho. Becket</hi> Arch <hi>B.</hi> of <hi>Cant</hi> an insolēt proud Prelate <hi>Lycost.</hi> p. 112.</note>
                     <hi>fall of great men from their power, who rule with pride and disdain. They also signifie (as others do conjecture) disturbances and innovations in matters of Religion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>There were two Suns seen in</hi> England <hi>at one time, shining at a good distance from each other in the beginning of Queen</hi> Maries <hi>raign: See</hi> Bakers <hi>Chron.</hi> p. 346.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Several Suns were seen near</hi> Prague, <hi>about the time of the dreadful persecution which the Protestants sustained there from the hands of the bloody Papists. See</hi> Bohem. <hi>Hist.</hi> p. 335.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The likenesse of a ship seen in the Air at <hi>Stratford-bow</hi> near 1441 0146 V 2 <hi>London.</hi>
                     </note>IN the same month was seen also at <hi>Stratford Bow</hi> near <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> the likenesse of a great Ship in the Air, which by degrees lessened till it came to be as small as a mans Arm, but kept its form all the while, and at last disappeared. This is testifyed
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152943:8"/>by an able Minister living not far from the place; who recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the information from the spectators themselves.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A Raln-bow of a blood-red colour seen before Sun-ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, at <hi>Southo</hi> in <hi>Huntington<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire.</hi>
                     </note>ABout the same time at <hi>Southo</hi> in <hi>Huntintonshire,</hi> was seen before Sun-rising, in the West and by North, a Rain-bow of a blood-red colour, it gave forth brightnesse as if the Sun had been rising in that part of the Heavens, after it had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued for a while, a great red cloud by degrees swallowed it up. This is testified by a very credible person who lived not farre from <hi>Southo,</hi> and did speak with several who were eye-witnesses.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>A Gentleman of good quality, and an Officer of Eminency in the late Kings Army,<note place="margin">Seven Stars seen to fall down perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicularly.</note> and now a Justice of Peace in the Country, having occasion to be at <hi>London</hi> about the month of <hi>September,</hi> 1660 as he was going over <hi>Smithfield</hi> about ten of the Clock at night to his Lodgings in <hi>Bartholomow</hi>'s close, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving several people looking up into the Heavens,<note place="margin">It is a thing rarely heard of, that such exhalations should move perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obliquely which is their natural moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Vid Herm. Trismag. l.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 518.</note> did himself also look up and espied towards the South-west a bright Star of a more then ordinary bignesse, and encompassed with six lesser Stars; whilst he with several others, were with some ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration beholding them, they all fell down perpendicularly and vanished. This Gentlemans Lady being at the same time in her Lodgings, and looking out at the window, expecting her Husbands coming, saw the same thing, with all the circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of it; a person of very good credit received this Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from both their Mouths.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>AT <hi>Hull</hi> about two of the clock in the morning, <hi>October</hi> 3. 1660. the Souldiers upon the Guard at the South Block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>house:<note place="margin">A great body of fire seen at <hi>Hull. Octob.</hi> 3. 1660.</note> the form of it (to use the Spectators own terms) was as big at one end as a great Sheet, from which went a narrow stream of Fire, which they judged to be many yards long: it gave such a light, that according to their report (though immediately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after it was very dark) yet they could see to read a very small print, or take up a pin from off the ground; this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued about the space of half an hour and then vanished.</p>
                  <p>The same morning also one Travelling from <hi>Lincolnshire</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152943:8"/>
                     <hi>Hull,</hi> saw a very great light in the sky, whereby he could perfectly discern his way, though before it was exceeding dark; this upon his Arrival at <hi>Hull</hi> that day, he affirmed to divers persons there. And the whole relation is signified by Letters from several eminent men in <hi>Hull</hi> who spake with the eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses, as also by some inhabitants of <hi>London,</hi> who upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion have been at <hi>Hull</hi> since that time, and there from very good hands have received credible and satisfactory information concerning the premises.<note place="margin">A Rain-bow seen between 11 and 12 of the clock at night, <hi>Octob.</hi> 5. 1660. <hi>Plin. Nat. Hist. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 59. <hi>Zanch.</hi> says that this <hi>Iris Lunaris</hi> differs from the other in respect of the colour; for in this he says there is but <hi>unos tantum co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor albus nimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Vid</hi> Zane. <hi>de operibus dei.</hi> p 353. He says it por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends <hi>longam tempestatem aurum{que} insta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilem. ibid.</hi> p. 356. A strange Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met seen at <hi>Hertford Octob.</hi> 11. 1660.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OCtober</hi> 5. 1660. between 11 and 12 a Clock at night, was seen near the new Artillery ground, a fair Rainbow with the usual Colours in it, that did seem to stand directly over the Moon, which at that time did shine extraordinary bright. The information we received from a very credible person was an eye-witnesse.</p>
                  <p>Pliny <hi>makes it an impossible thing in nature, that a Rain-bow should be at any time seen in the Night, though he confesseth that</hi> Aristotle <hi>doth affirm, that once such a thing happened, but it was when the Moon was at full. But if what</hi> Aristotle <hi>sayes is true,</hi> (<hi>which</hi> Pliny <hi>much questions</hi>) <hi>yet still what hath been above rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted concering the Rain-bow seen in the night when the Moon was not at Full, must needs acknowledge it to be no ordinary thing: the meaning</hi> and import whereof, the Lord may in due time discover; which we pray that he will turn for good to all that tremble at his word and works.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>A Person of very good Note and Credit living at <hi>Hertford,</hi> awaking about 4 of the Clock in the Morning, <hi>Octob.</hi> 11. 1660. perceived a flashing like fire against his window, and fearing some house near him had been on fire, he immediately arose and went to the Window, and looking up perceived a Star about the bignesse of the palm of his hand, it had a dusky Circle about it, two straiks near half a yard long a piece went through the midst of it, which both above and below did send forth continually great Flashes of Fire; it stood directly North and South, and on the South side of it, was a point about half a quarter of a yard long, this continued for some hours and then
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152943:9"/>disappeared; it was seen also by several other credible persons at <hi>Hertford,</hi> from whom this Relation comes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>MUch about the same time was seen by several persons near <hi>Hornsy,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A <hi>meteor</hi> in the form of a Dart seen hanging over <hi>London.</hi> This is by the Philosopher cal'd <hi>Bolis. Vid Magiri. Physol.</hi> l. 4. <hi>c.</hi> 2. Two Meteors like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Ship-streamer or a Beesom seen in <hi>Woodstreet, Octob.</hi> 12. 1660.</note> a Flame of Fire in the form of a Dart; which according to the apprehensions of the Spectators hung directly over the City of <hi>London.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>IX.</head>
                  <p>IN <hi>Woodstreet, London,</hi> upon the 12. of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1660. about four of the Clock in the Afternoon, was seen by several of the Inhabitants there, a fiery Meteor in the fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m of a Ship-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, or as others apprehended of a Beesome, with the great end formost, about two yards in length; it passed with a ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> swift motion from West to East, And as some of the Spectators do affirm, it made a great noise as it passed by; immediately upon it followed another of the same form, but not of the same big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. The Information comes from eye-witnesses.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Such a prodigious sign in this Form, though of longer continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, appeared in</hi> Anno 1550. <hi>when the persecution began to wax hot in</hi> Scotland <hi>against the Professors of the Truth.</hi> Vid. <hi>Clark</hi>'s Prodigies, <hi>pag.</hi> 490.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>AT <hi>Shenley</hi> in <hi>Hertfordshire</hi> (<hi>Octob.</hi> 17. 1660. being the day wherein Colonel <hi>Scroop,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Five naked Men seen in the Air at <hi>Shenley, Octob.</hi> 17. 1660.</note> Col. <hi>Jones,</hi> and some others were Executed at <hi>Charing-cross</hi>) was seen in the Air towards the Evening, the Sky being very clear, the appearance of Five na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Men exceeding bright and glorious, moving very swiftly, and after a little time a great Hill intercepted the sight of them. The Report of this was received from an Eye-witnesse, who is not in the least suspected to be a Phanatique, but hath given evident proof to the contrary; he doth constantly affirm the Truth of it, and offers to confirm it by his Oath.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A bright Star appearing at noon-day over the Quarters which were set up upon <hi>Algate.</hi>
                     </note>NOt long after this <hi>viz.</hi> the same day when the Quarters of the several Executed persons were set up upon the Gates of the City, there appeared at Noon-day, a bright Star over <hi>Algate,</hi> for two or three hours together, and continued so for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152943:9"/>4 or 5 dayes; Of this many hundreds in the City passing that way, together with the adjacent Inhabitants were dayly Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors during the time before specified.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Seven Pillars of Smoke seen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scending from the <hi>Quarters</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Bishops gate.</hi> Two <hi>Quarters</hi> more having been since set upon the same Gate. Three <hi>Moons</hi> were seen at <hi>Titsie</hi> in <hi>Surrey Octo.</hi> 19. 1660.</note>ALso at <hi>Bishops gate</hi> there appeared seven Pillars of smoke (one whereof was bigger then the rest) ascending from the seven Quarters which were first set up upon the Gate; they reached up towards Heaven as high as the beholders could well discern.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <p>AT <hi>Titsie</hi> in <hi>Surrey, Octob.</hi> 29. 1660. about 8 or 9 of the Clock in the Evening, there appeared in the Heavens three Moons of equal bignesse and brightnesse at a little distance from each other. The Relation come from eye-witnesses, who were many, and some of good Note and Quality.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In</hi> Ireland, Anno 1342. October 11, <hi>the Moon being</hi> 11 <hi>days old, were seen at</hi> Dublin, <hi>two Moons.</hi> Camb. Britt. Ireland, p. 188. <hi>Also in the Month of</hi> March, Anno 1551. <hi>in the year wherein the Duke of</hi> Somerset <hi>was beheaded, and the Disputes were in</hi> Germany <hi>about Religion, and the</hi> French <hi>made war with the Emperour, three Moons were seen together here in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. <hi>The like happened also</hi> Annis 1644, 1645, 1646, 1647. <hi>The like happened a little before the bloody Wars between the</hi> Romans <hi>and</hi> Carthaginians <hi>brake forth.</hi> Livius <hi>Hist.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="section">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A fiery Meteor seen near <hi>Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> in <hi>Hert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>dshire,</hi> from which did fall down perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ly three Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s, whereby the Earth was exceedingly enlightned. The Meteor afterwards tu n'd into the form of a <hi>sickle</hi> and then into the Form of a Sythe.</note>THree persons inhabitants of <hi>Austy</hi> in <hi>Hertfordshire</hi> going before Day, <hi>Octob.</hi> 30. 1660. with Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t-horses to <hi>Ware-Market,</hi> were on a sudden smitten with a terrible Flash of Lightning; after which the Air continued very light, and grew brighter and brighter, and they looking from whence this great light should come, saw, as they conceived, full East before them, a very dreadful Fire, and concluded that some House at <hi>Meisden</hi> had been on Fire; but they having not ridden much further, perceived the Fire in a great Body to Ascend, and the Sky opening to receive it; and as it went up, three Stars one immediately after another fell down from it perpendicularly; and when they fell, the Earth seemed lighter then at any
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152943:10"/>time by the brightest Moon-light. Some part of the Body of Fire which ascended, remained yet in their View, and after a little space, it turned into the direct Form of a Sickle with a handle, and afterwards it grew much like to a Syth, &amp; continu'd in that Form till the Day-light swallowed it up. The Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors are very credible Persons from whom this Relation comes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="section">
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A fiery Meteor in the Form of a Dragon seen between <hi>Had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> and <hi>Ware, Octob.</hi> 30. 1660.</note>THe same Morning also some going before Day with their Carts, from about <hi>Hadham</hi> side in <hi>Hertfordshire</hi> to <hi>Ware,</hi> saw a Body of Fire in the Sky, of divers colours like the Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow, which presently turn'd into the perfect Form of a Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon, and immediately fell down to the ground, and by the fall of it, the Earth was so lightned, that they could have seen a penny upon the Ground, as the Spectators themselves do affirm, From whom we have this whole Relation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This kind of Meteor is called by the Philosopher</hi> Draco Volans. <hi>And about the time of the</hi> Bohemian <hi>Persecution,</hi> viz. <hi>in the year</hi> 1624. <hi>such a fiery Dragon was seen throughout all</hi> Bohemia <hi>and</hi> Silesia, Vid. Bohem. <hi>Hist. p.</hi> 356. <hi>The like also was seen in</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Novemb. 25. 1656. <hi>which was confirmed by several Letters from thence at that time, a true and full Description of it; toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Portends thereof you in a Book called</hi> Miraculum Signum Coeleste, <hi>page</hi> 28.29, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="section">
                  <head>XVI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A Body of fire ascending into the Air till it fixed it self in the Sky like a Star seen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Hert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> &amp; <hi>London, Octob.</hi> 30. 1660.</note>THe same morning likewise before day when it was very dark, five Neighbours going from <hi>Hertford</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> did alight by the way and walked to get themselves a heat, and as they were getting up upon their Horses again, there came a sudden Flash of Fire which made it so light, that they could perfectly discern as at noon day any thing upon the ground, their Horses also seemed to be all on fire; but within a little space this Body of Fire rose up again into the Air, with a Tayl about a Pole long, and went Eastward, where at last it fixed it self in the Sky like a Star.<note place="margin">A ball of fire was seen to come but of the Heavens and fel upon a Gentlemans House.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="section">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <p>UPon the same morning very early the Waggoner of <hi>Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks</hi> came towards <hi>London</hi> with his Waggon and divers Passengers in it, about a mile from <hi>Wickham</hi>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152943:10"/>they all saw to their great afrightment, the Heavens open,<note place="margin">Another fell upon a wood. And a third upon the Ground. These were seen <hi>Octob.</hi> 30. 1660.</note> and a large Ball of Fire about the bignesse (to use the Relaters own phrase) of a great Kittle, in a terrible manner descending and falling as they conceived upon a Gentlemans house near a quarter of a mile from them, and they verily thought, because the fire brake in pieces on the house, it had been set on fire by it, but afterwards they found it to be otherwise: immediately upon this they saw another ball of fire descending in the same manner with the former, which fell upon a Wood very near to the Road wherein they were travelling, and they conceived that the whole Wood had been in a flame: A third ball also came down and fell upon the Earth and was broken into several pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; during this time which was about the space of half an hour the Air was exceeding light, so that the Passengers in the Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon could perfectly discern each other, and see to read an or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry Print, but immediately after it was as dark as before. This Relation comes from some of the aforesaid Passengers par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly from the Waggoner and his Wife.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="section">
                  <head>XVIII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A fiery Mete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or with a Tail 30 yards long, seen between <hi>Ʋxbridge</hi> and <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>anford, Octo.</hi> 30. 1660.</note>SEveral persons on the same 30 of <hi>October</hi> going from <hi>Ʋx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bride</hi> to <hi>Brainford</hi> between 3 and 4 of the Clock in the morning, saw in the Sky a very great light standing East and West; that part towards the East was as broad as a very large Table; that part towards the West seemed to them to be a Tail of about 30 yards long as near as they could guesse, it did so enlighten the air that they could see to read the smallest Print, It continued till near break of day, and then divided in the middle, half went to the East, and half to the West, and so by degrees disappeared; several Inhabitants of <hi>Ʋxbridge</hi> in their journey to <hi>Brainford</hi> and others at home in their houses were eye-witnesses hereof, and did relate it to a Citizen of <hi>London</hi> a person of known worth and integrity, from whom we received this Information.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Meteor much like this in form was seen near</hi> Bristow <hi>in the month of</hi> January,<note place="margin">The Paralel.</note> Anno 1648. <hi>which is published in print by an able godly Minister in</hi> London, <hi>who received the information from an eye-witnesse.</hi> Vid <hi>Clarks</hi> Prod. <hi>p.</hi> 483.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="section">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:152943:11"/>
                  <head>XIX.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A great bright star seen at <hi>Yelden</hi> in <hi>Bedfordshire, Octo.</hi> 30. 1660.</note>AT <hi>Yelden</hi> in <hi>Bedfordshire</hi> the same morning very early was seen a great Star which stood North-East and South-West, it gaue so great a light, that some inhabitants there, who were up so soon that morning upon their occasions could see to doe businesse in the house by the light of it; one credible person there beheld it two hours together, and at last see it turn into the perfect form of a Roman S, and then presently it divided in the middle, and one half went to the North-east, and the other to the South-west, and so by degrees disappeared. Two other persons of credit in <hi>Northamptonshire,</hi> not many miles from <hi>Yelden,</hi> saw the same morning a very great light in their chamber which they much wondred at, because it was not the time for the Moon to shine, but they not rising out of their beds saw not the Star as others did from whom this relation comes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Paralel.</note>
                     <hi>In the year</hi> 389. <hi>a little before the</hi> Scots <hi>and the</hi> Picts <hi>invaded</hi> Brittain, <hi>did arise in the North a great Star much bigger then the day-star, and shined several mornings together,</hi> viz. <hi>discourse of Prod.</hi> p. 88.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="section">
                  <head>XX.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A fiery Mete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or seen near <hi>Pickadilla</hi> a fligh-shot in length and 5 foot in bredth, <hi>Octo.</hi> 30. 1660.</note>ABout five of the Clock in the morning the same 30 of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1660. two persons of credit living near <hi>Pickadilla,</hi> going over the field by the <hi>Pall-mall,</hi> heard a noise in the Air, as if a pound of Gunpowder had been fired; and looking up they saw a body of fire bigger then the Moon, from which there issued a stream of fire towards the East a flight-shot in length and 5 foot in bredth; There were also two shorter streams of fire issuing from the same body South-east and South. This relation comes from one of those two persons who were the eye-witnesses.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="section">
                  <head>XXI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A fiery Meteor seen <hi>Octob.</hi> 30. 1660. near <hi>Harleston,</hi> which grew into the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion and shape of a man and then va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished.</note>SEveral considerable persons near <hi>Harleston</hi> in <hi>Norfolk</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 4 and 5 of the clock in the morning on the aforesaid 30 of <hi>Octob.</hi> saw a very great fire in the Air flaming every way, and sparkling exceedingly, it seemed to them to roll up and down in the Air: and it gave so great a light, that one of the Relaters saith he could see to do any work as well as if he had many Torches by him. This fiery Meteor after a while, as the Spectators conceived, grew into the proportion and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152943:11"/>shape of a man, and continued so for an hour, and then by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees disappeared.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="section">
                  <head>XXII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Another fiery Meteor seen between <hi>Ips<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich</hi> &amp; <hi>Thwayt Octob.</hi> 30. 1660.</note>TWo Inhabitants of <hi>Ipswich</hi> travelling between 3 and 4 of the clock in the same morning towards <hi>Thwayt</hi> saw very strange and terrible flashes of Lightning, and looking up they discerned in the Sky two great balls of Fire, the one North-east, which was the greatest, the other South-west; the first gly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding downward, divided it self into small pieces sparkling, and after a while gathered up it self into a body again, and then turned into a Cloud of a blood-red colour, and soon after va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished. They were so intent upon this in the North-east that they can give no account what became of that which appeared in the South-west. These two last particulars we received in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of from a very worthy person who had an account of them from the Spectators themselves, men of repute and credit in the places of their habitation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="section">
                  <head>XXIII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of three Heads seen in a bright cloud between <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurst</hi> and <hi>Chichester.</hi>
                     </note>ABout the same day an Inhabitant of <hi>Midhurst</hi> in the County of <hi>Sussex</hi> going to <hi>Chichester</hi> about 10 of the Clock in the forenoon, beheld one end of a Cloud exceeding bright like to the Sun it self, and presently there appeared the likeness of a head with well set hair, &amp; by it immediately appeared another head and so a Third, but they all quickly vanished away together.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="section">
                  <head>XXIV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A groat light covering the grou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d for a mile in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passe, and then asc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nding like a pil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ar of fire, in which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared an arm brandishing a flaming sword.</note>ABout the beginning of <hi>Novemb.</hi> certain Tradesmen going to <hi>Thame</hi> Faire, about two of the clock in the morning as they passed between the two <hi>Wickhams</hi> saw a very great Light upon the Ground, spreading it self near a mile in compass, very dreadful and terrible to behold, insomuch that many of them apprehended that the day of judgement was come; afterwards it gathered up into a Pillar of Fire, and therein they clearly discerned an Army brandishing a Flaming Sword.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="section">
                  <head>XXV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Two stars as big as the Moon seen contesting each with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. and one of them did seem to pour down Blood and fire successively.</note>TWo men coming from about <hi>Avery Hatch</hi> near <hi>Ilford</hi> in <hi>Essex</hi> towards <hi>London,</hi> very early in the morning, <hi>Novemb.</hi> 5. 1660. saw in the South-west a fiery bright Cloud, which in a little time was dispersed, and from under it appeared two
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152943:12"/>Stars as big as the Moon, and to their apprehensions they did with great violence contend each with other; and after they had contested a while one the Stars by degrees grew dimmer and lesser, and the other brighter and larger, till at length one of them totally disappeared, the other continued in their sight at least two hours, a great part of which time they saw streaming from it as they conceived successively streams of fire and streams of blood, and (to use their own words) the blood streamed from it as if it had been poured out of a Payl or Bucket. This Star afterwards by degrees lessened till it came to the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an ordinary Star, and so continued till they entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>White-Chappel.</hi> All this was received from the mouths of the Spectators by many persons of eminency in <hi>London,</hi> both that morning they came to Town, and at several times fince.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="section">
                  <head>XXVI.</head>
                  <p>SEveral Persons in <hi>Spittle-field, Novemb.</hi> 6. 1660. and so for many mornings together about seven of the Clock,<note place="margin">A great S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ar of divers co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours seen in <hi>Spittle fields, Novemb.</hi> 6. 1660. and at several other times.</note> have seen in the heavens a very strange Star much bigger then the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Star; those who looked upon it through a Prospective-Glasse (and amongst them the person from whom we received the account was one) could easily discern it to be of three se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral colours; on the one part it was blewish like the flaming of Brimstone, in the middle it was clear like the usual colour of a Star, and on the opposite part it was like the Flame of a smoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fire.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="section">
                  <head>XXVII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Fire appearing upon Horses Heads and on Travellers Switches as they rode between <hi>Hull</hi> and <hi>Beverly</hi> in a great storm of Thunder and Lightning, <hi>November</hi> 10. 1660.</note>BY Letters from persons of very good credit, Inhabitants of <hi>Hull,</hi> it is certified, that on the 10 of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1660. there was about six of the Clock in the Evening, a very sore and dreadful Thunder and Lightning, some that were riding that Evening from <hi>Beuerly</hi> to <hi>Hull</hi> and other places, thought that their Horses heads and the sticks in their Fellow-travellers hands had been of a light fire.</p>
                  <p>This is somewhat like to that which by Philosophers is called <hi>Ignis Lambens,</hi> which they say is <hi>plane prodigiosum &amp; sine omni causa Physica. Magiri. Phis.</hi> 4. Lib, 4. Cap. 2.</p>
                  <p>Also by other Letters out of <hi>York-shire</hi> from very good hands, we are assured that about the same time there hath been very sore Thundring and Lightning to the great terror and amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152943:12"/>of the Inhabitans; whereof the more notice is to be taken, because such Tempests are not usual at that season of the year.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="section">
                  <head>XXVIII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Armies seen in the Heavens engaged in Fight against each other.</note>
                     <hi>SEveral credible persons, Inhabitants of</hi> Harsham <hi>in</hi> Sussex, <hi>coming towards</hi> London <hi>very early in the Morning, as they were riding throw</hi> Smithans bottom <hi>near</hi> Croyden, <hi>on a sudden saw a very great Light, and the Hill on their left hand appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as it had been all on a Flame: in a little time that great light divided it self into two distinct lights, wherein seemed to them to be two distinct Armies engaging and pushing one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the other; they beheld them in this posture a very consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable space of time, till at last there fell an exceeding thick Fog which made it very dark, and the smell of the Fog was as the smell of Gunpowder. This Relation was received by a Contributor to this Collection from an eye-witnesse.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Paralel.</note>Prodigies like to this have at several times happened in many places, &amp; the events hath been alwaies very signal &amp; remarkable.</p>
                  <p>Thus did God forewarn the Jews of the distruction of themselves, their City and Temple which was effected not long after by <hi>Titus Vespasian</hi> See Joseph. Lib. <hi>7. of the Jewish Wars,</hi> Cap. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The like also appeared in <hi>England Anno 1415,</hi> not long before that Famous fight at <hi>Agen Court</hi> in <hi>France</hi> wherein the <hi>English</hi> slew upon the place <hi>10000 French,</hi> and took as many Prisoners. <hi>Vid.</hi> Signum Caeleste, <hi>&amp;c. p 126.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>About the same time also Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> died, <hi>ibid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The great alteration of state and the prosecution of bloody wars in <hi>Italy</hi> by <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>8.</hi> King of <hi>France;</hi> was portended and foresigned (amongst other things) by the apparition of great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of men, joyning battle over <hi>Aretium,</hi> a Town in <hi>Tuscany</hi> says Dr. <hi>Jackson</hi> in a Sermon of his before the late King <hi>Charles,</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>the Signs of the time, on</hi> Luke <hi>13.5. p. 12.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the Low Countries, <hi>Anno 1588.</hi> Armies were often seen in the Heavens; and not long after the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> brought an Army into the field against Duke <hi>De Alva</hi> in behalf of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants. and through the blessing of God was instrumental thereby to deliver that people from so cruel and bloody a persecutor, <hi>Strada.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The people in <hi>Germany</hi> were often spectators of the like Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies, and they were still the forerunners of some bloody Fights, Skirmishes, or Sieges, at or near those places where they were first seen. Thus it happened at <hi>Lint. 2</hi> in <hi>Austria,</hi> as you may see
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152943:13"/>at large in the <hi>Germ.</hi> Prod. <hi>p. 10. 11.</hi> and so also in <hi>Silesia, ibid. p. 17. 18.</hi> But more especially in the year, <hi>1628.</hi> at <hi>Sunderbury</hi> in <hi>Pomerland</hi> two Armies appeared in the Heavens, the one from the North the other from the South; they engaged against each other till the Army from the North seemed totally to rout and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy the other. About two years after, the Renowned <hi>Gustavus Adolphus</hi> King of <hi>Sweden</hi> landed his Army from the North near the place before mentioned and not far from it did engage with the Imperial Army, &amp; totally vanquished it. <hi>Vid. Germ.</hi> Prod. p. <hi>31. 32.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The like was seen also <hi>June 18. 1631.</hi> At <hi>Asherleban</hi> in the lower <hi>Saxony:</hi> not long after between the said Town and <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>germund,</hi> the <hi>Swedes</hi> did great execution upon the Imperialists; and so at several other times within that year to the almost utter destruction of <hi>Tillyes</hi> Gallant Army, which you may read at large in the <hi>Germ.</hi> prod. <hi>p. 44. 45, 46.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We our selves also in <hi>England</hi> have of late times known this kind of apparition, and by too sad experience felt the meaning of it. It is fresh in the memory of many, that in <hi>Anno 1640.</hi> not long before our unhappy civil Wars, Armies were seen in the Heavens divers times and in divers places by many discreet persons of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, which, sayes an Author, were looked upon as sad presages of the ensuing broils <hi>Baker</hi> Chron. p. <hi>493. 494</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The coming in and the defeating of Duke <hi>Hambletons</hi> Army, <hi>Anno 1648.</hi> was clearly portended by the appearance in the Heavens of a Southern and Northren Army in <hi>Yorkshire,</hi> and the Northern Armies being beaten by the other. The truth whereof many yet alive can testifie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="section">
                  <head>XXIX.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A great bright Star as big as the Moon seen in <hi>Hounds ditch Decemb.</hi> 1. 1660.</note>AN honest man an Inhabitant in <hi>Hounsditch</hi> near <hi>Bishopsgate,</hi> affirms that on the 1. of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1660. about 5 of the Clock in the Morning, he saw in the East a very bright Star as big as the Moon; he called up several of his Family to see it, who also were eye-witnesses of it with himself; from whom immediately we received this information.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="30" type="section">
                  <head>XXX.</head>
                  <p>A Citizen of good Note in <hi>London,</hi> having occasion to stay all night,<note place="margin">A great bright Star seen at <hi>Stoke New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ington, Decemb.</hi> 5. 1660.</note>
                     <hi>Decemb.</hi> 4. 1660. at <hi>Stoke-Newington,</hi> in the Morning about 5 of the Clock, saw a very great Light in his Chamber, and being much amazed at it, he arose out of his bed and went to the window, and looking out he saw towards
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152943:13"/>the East, a very great bright twinkling Star, as big (according to his own relation) as many six Stars that he ever saw be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it shone so bright that he could have seen to read or doe any other business in his Chamber by the Light of it; He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held it a quarter of an hour, and being very cold returned to his bed again. This Relation we have from the Gentlemans own mouth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel.</note>
                     <hi>In the year</hi> 1572. <hi>there appeared in</hi> Cathedra Cassiopeae, <hi>a large bright Star (though not so big as either of these two last mentioned,) the effect whereof was seen in a very great darth of Corn, as also all other provisions.</hi> Baker. <hi>Chron. p.</hi> 422.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="31" type="section">
                  <head>XXXI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Several Stee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrals seen burning in the Air, some sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, others torn irrepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note>IT is Certified by a Letter from a very good hand in <hi>York<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> that six sober discreet persons being very early upon the Road, saw a fiery Apparition in the Aire, wherein they discerned 2 or 3 Steeples and several Cathedrals, some burning, others rent and torn irreparably, others subverted with the Pinacles downwards, and by one of the Pinacles stood an Angel with a flaming Sword.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="32" type="section">
                  <head>XXXII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A Steeple fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the Air, and tumbled down with a Sword hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at it. Another Stee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple fired also, and tumbled down with a Pike hanging at it.</note>BY another Letter also from a person of Credit in <hi>Yorkshire,</hi> to an Eminent Citizen in <hi>London,</hi> it is certified that a little before the last great Wind which hapned <hi>Decemb.</hi> 8. 1660. There was seen in <hi>Bramma More</hi> in <hi>Yorkshire,</hi> the Form of a Steeple in the Sky, which presently grew red, and then the Heavens seemed to open, and great Flashes of Fire proceeded out and fired the Steeple, which presently tumbled down with a long Cross-hilted Sword hanging at it; Also at the same time &amp; place was seen the Form of a Church all on fire, which tumbled down as the other with a long Pike hanging at it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="33" type="section">
                  <head>XXXIII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A standing Field of Corn seen in the Heavens near <hi>Horsey Downs,</hi> and Reapers coming forth to reap it.</note>ABout the latter end of <hi>December</hi> last, at <hi>Horsey Downs</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 2 and 3 a clock in the morning, several credible persons saw the Heavens open, and there appeared a standing Field of Corn, and reapers coming forth to reap it with Sickles in their hands, and a Lyon standing over the Reapers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="34" type="section">
                  <head>XXXIV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A Sheet of fire mingled with blood, seen directly over <hi>Paul's, Jan.</hi> 14. 1660.</note>ABout the 14 of <hi>January</hi> last, betwixt two and three of the Clock in the morning, there appeared a very great Light
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152943:14"/>over the City of <hi>London,</hi> some persons of credit dwelling in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noster row,</hi> being up, upon some occasion so early that morning, went forth and saw as they have since related directly over <hi>Pauls</hi> a sheet of Fire mingled with blood, the Spectators acquainted some of us herewith.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="35" type="section">
                  <head>XXXV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A fiery Sword over the west-part of <hi>London, Jan.</hi> 22. 1660.</note>
                     <hi>AT</hi> Hogsden <hi>near</hi> London, Jan. <hi>22. 1660. in the Evening was seen by several honest discreet persons, a very great Light towards the South-west, some of the Spectators thought that some part of the City of</hi> Westminster <hi>had been on fire; After they had for a little space of time viewed this fiery Light, they plainly observed to come out of it a long white Streak in the Form of a Sword pointing towards the North-west. This Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation we received from a very honest credible person an eye-witnesse.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>An Apparition not altogether unlike this was seen over <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem</hi> not long after the Destruction of it by <hi>Titus Vespasian,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel.</note>
                     <hi>Joseph.</hi> Hist. of the Jewes Wars. <hi>Lib. 7. Chap. 12.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Over the City <hi>Bribrech</hi> on the <hi>6.</hi> of <hi>March, 1632.</hi> in the Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, was seen in the Air, a long fiery Sword; the next year <hi>Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stavus Horn</hi> the <hi>Swedish</hi> Field-Marshall did defeat the Catholick Army, killed many, and took the said City after the Inhabitants had been brought to miserable extremities. <hi>Vid. Ger. Prod,</hi> p. <hi>52. 53.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Such a Sword was seen over <hi>Rome</hi> a little before it was taken by the <hi>Goths,</hi> and so great a slaughter made of the <hi>Romans</hi> as the like was never known in any Age before. <hi>Lycost.</hi> p. <hi>286.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="36" type="section">
                  <head>XXXVI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A great Fire seen in the Air over the <hi>white Tower.</hi>
                     </note>AN inhabitant in the Town much about the same time, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving occasion to be out of his house about 12 of the clock at night, saw a very great Fire in the Air directly over the White Tower; He presently called forth some others to behold it, who also were eye-witnesses with him thereof, from one of whom we received this Information.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="37" type="section">
                  <head>XXXVII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Strange flash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Fire seen in the Air over <hi>Govent-Garden.</hi>
                     </note>THere are probable Reports of several other strange Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritions that were seen about the same time over White Tower; But because we have no clear nor certain proof of them, only this is most true, that several inhabitants in the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, did in the Months of <hi>January</hi> and <hi>February</hi> for several
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152943:14"/>Evenings together see a very strange and unusual flashings of Fire in the Air over <hi>Covent Garden</hi> and the parts adjacent.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="38" type="section">
                  <head>XXXVIII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A blazing Star seen over <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>ABout the latter end of</hi> January <hi>and the beginning of</hi> Febr. <hi>1660. was seen by divers credible persons over</hi> Westmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>a blazing Star, which continued several nights together; It is likewise most certainly true, that in the month of</hi> October <hi>and since, hath been sometimes in the East, sometimes in the South-west, sometimes in the East and South-west, a Comet or blazing Star, between 3 and 4 of the Clock in the morning, this hath been observed by very many discreet and sober persons in and about</hi> London, <hi>as also in divers other places in this Nation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the year <hi>1660.</hi> a Comet or blazing Star appeared to the People in this Land,<note place="margin">The Parallel.</note> and not long after <hi>Wil.</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy</hi> defeating King <hi>Harold</hi> and his Army, obtained the Crown of <hi>England. Stow.</hi> Chron. <hi>p. 98, 99.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ʋpon that blazing Star and the Effects thereof were made the following Verses.</p>
                  <p>A Thousand six and sixty years, It was as we do read,</p>
                  <p>When that a Comet did appear, And English men lay dead;</p>
                  <p>Of <hi>Normandy,</hi> Duke <hi>William</hi> then, To <hi>England</hi> ward did sail,</p>
                  <p>Who conquer'd <hi>Harold</hi> &amp; his men, &amp; brought this land to bail. <hi>ibid.</hi> p. <hi>101.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the year also <hi>1401</hi> was seen a blazing Star, which says my Author, did perhaps foreshew the effusion of blood which followed after in <hi>Wales</hi> and <hi>Northumberland,</hi> See <hi>Baker Chron. p. 178.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anno 1580 Octob. 10</hi> or <hi>7</hi> Comet was seen, and not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Pope sends several companies of <hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>Spaniards</hi> to the aid of the Earl of <hi>Destmund</hi> in his Rebellion in <hi>Ireland;</hi> but they were soon through the blessing of God Defeated, and many hundreds of them put to the Sword, <hi>Stow. Chron. p. 668.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We need not mention the Comet seen in the year <hi>1618,</hi> and what bloody wars did ensue immediately both in <hi>Germany, Poland, Italy</hi> &amp; indeed all the Christian world over, whereof you may read at large in <hi>Stow</hi> &amp; many other famous Chronologies &amp; historians.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="39" type="section">
                  <head>XXXIX.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Fire was seen to fly over <hi>Derby.</hi>
                     </note>MUch about the same time by letters from very credible persons living at <hi>Derby,</hi> we are assured that there was seen in the Air a great body of fire as big as two or three ordinary
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152943:15"/>houses, which to the very great terror and afrightment of the Inhabitants, did fly over the Town of <hi>Derby,</hi> and caused such a light that one might have seen to have taken up a pin by the light of it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="40" type="section">
                  <head>XL</head>
                  <p>ABout the end of this month of <hi>January,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Strange and terrible noises heard in the Air as of beating of Drums, the reports of great and small Guns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> a person of honesty and discretion by the importunity of some of his Children who had been abroad, was prevailed with to go forth to take notice of a strange noise which his Children told him they had heard in the Air; Upon this going forth he did hear a strange rushing noise, and that he might the better satisfie himself about it, he went further into an open Field not far from his house, where he plainly saw toward the North a black Cloud, and in the Clould he heard a great rushing noise as of a shower of Rain or Hail; but about the Cloud he saw the Sky was very clear, After a little space of time he heard perfectly the sound of a Drum beating in the Cloud, and after that the report of great and small Guns which continued for a long time; afterwards about that black Cloud, where before it was very clear, there appeared many small Clouds which flying swiftly every way did smite and dash one against another; He looked at it till he was weary, and then returned to his house, and in his way thither did still hear the noise of Drums and Guns as before.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This Prodigy happened in</hi> Austria <hi>in the year</hi> 1621. <hi>and the month of</hi> March, <hi>and not long after near the place where those noises were heard, very bloody Skirmishes and Fights were between the</hi> Swedes <hi>and the</hi> Imperialists, Germ. Prod. p. 10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is generally known that these kind of Noises were often heard in the Air in several parts of</hi> England, <hi>not long before the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy breaking out of our civil VVars.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And in the year</hi> 1658 Octob. 10. <hi>the noise of Guns and Drums was heard in the Air by many considerable persons in York-shire about</hi> Holdernesse, Holden, Heddon, Patrington, &amp;c. <hi>and seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall other places; it continued about half an hour, during which time, there was a great mist in the Air like smoak, and the earth seemed to quake and tremble; This thing is so generally received as a truth in those parts, there being yet alive so many that heard it, that it is above all contradiction.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="41" type="section">
                  <head>XL.</head>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:152943:15"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A Meteor in the Heavens like a sheaf of Corn on a burning flame.</note>IN the month of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1660. A Citizen of note, with some other Passengers came from Gravesend in a night that was so dark that the water-men lost their way, and in 6 hours time had not gone above 4 or 5 miles; in the midst of this darkness, there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared a fearful fire in the Heavens, which brake forth like a sheaf of corn all on a burning flame, and continued so about the space of a quarter of an hour, then was it obscured for the space about half a quarter of an hour, and after that flamed again near a quarter of an hour, and afterwards disappeared. The Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on comes from the aforesaid Citizen one of the Passengers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="42" type="section">
                  <head>XLI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of two Churches in the Heavens, the one like a Cathedral, the other a very 0536 0 small one, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note>ABout the 26. of <hi>Feb.</hi> last, a discreet sober Gentleman, and 0536 of good quality, an inhabitant of the Town of <hi>Darken</hi> in <hi>Surrey,</hi> being abroad in the Evening, saw a strange cloud in the Air, &amp; in it the appearance of two Churches, the one was in the form of a Cathedral, very spatious and glorious, having upon it divers goodly Pinacles, and each of them a long streamer fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upwards upon it, aad as he beheld it, he thought it grew up to a greater splendor and glory, glittering and shining exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly; he saw also not far from it (which he could scarcely dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern) another Church which was very mean and little in res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the former, and he especially observed, that when the great Church was most glorious, then the little one was most dark and obscure, yet he plainly discerned a very bright star in the midst of it, and another bright star between the two Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; after this Gentleman had for some time with great admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration beheld this strange apparition, he perceived a small puffe as of b eath upon the stately Cathedral Church, and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately it fell down and vanished away; Then he saw the little Church with the star begin to appear more bright and glorious, but upon some special occasion being earnestly called into his house, he saw not the issue of it, which since hath been a very great trouble to him; This comes from the Spectators one mouth, who hath been alwaies observed to be very averse to give the least credit to relations of this nature, he was by his his own eyes convinced of the truth of this.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="43" type="section">
                  <head>XLII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A Flame of Fire seen over <hi>London.</hi>
                     </note>ABout 8 of the clock at night, 0536 0208 V <hi>March</hi> 14. 166<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, some of the Inhabitants of <hi>Plaistow</hi> in the Parish of <hi>We<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t-Ham</hi> near <hi>London,</hi> saw for some hours together a fiery great flame of fire
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152943:16"/>over the City of <hi>London,</hi> as near as they could guesse it was so great that a very knowing person, an eye-witness, (from whom we received this information) did declare to us, that he belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved he should the next morning have heard that half the City had been consumed by fire, but coming to <hi>London</hi> the next day, he found his fears prevented, though his admiration very much heightned.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Such fires were seen in many places Anno</hi> 1098. <hi>and sayes my Author,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Paralel.</note> secuta est animalium pestilentia, &amp; segetes nimio imbre &amp; aerugine corruptae sunt, <hi>there followed upon it a great pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and the spoiling of the fruits of the earth by too much rain and blasting,</hi> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cost. pag. 380. 390.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The like also happened in severall other places, with the like eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cts,</hi> Anno Mundi 3496. ibid. p. 75. 76.</p>
                  <p>Rome <hi>also was once taken, not long after such kind of Meteors were seen over it, though soon delivered again by</hi> Lucr. Liu. Hist.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The like Prodigy was seen a little before the great divisions hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened between the</hi> Patritii <hi>and the</hi> Plebeii <hi>in</hi> Rome, <hi>and so strong attempt were made to bring in the</hi> Decem viri, Anno Mundi, 3505, Licost. p. 73.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="44" type="section">
                  <head>XLIII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A bright cloud runing to and fro in the air, and dropping down fire up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>W. H</hi> and 0536 0 the <hi>P.</hi> H. <hi>March</hi> 14. 1660.</note>SEveral Passengers coming in a Boat from <hi>Putney</hi> to 0536 0 <hi>London,</hi> about 8 of the Clock at night, <hi>March</hi> 14 1660. when they were near <hi>Westminster</hi> saw a dark and black cloud hanging over <hi>W H</hi> which after a little space of time p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ssed away, and in the room of it appeared a white bright Cloud, which gave such a light that they could plainly discern the windows of the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament House, and people walking to and fro upon <hi>Westminster</hi> bridge, though before it was exceeding dark; whilst they beheld this Cloud, they saw it drop down fire several times upon <hi>W H</hi> and then it removed and stood over the <hi>P H</hi> and did drop down fire upon that also several times, then it removed back again to <hi>W H</hi> and dropt down fire again and then went back again to the <hi>P H.</hi> and did the like again there, and so continued to do it successively 4 or 5 times together, to the affrightment of the Passengers, but especially the Water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; One of the Gentlemen that was in the Boat came (as we have been informed) that night to <hi>W H</hi> and related this story to several persons there, the same apparition was seen at the same time &amp; over the same places by divers Travellers that came from <hi>Kensington</hi> towards <hi>London</hi> that night.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="45" type="section">
                  <head>XLIV.</head>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:152943:16"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A fiery Mete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or breaking into several pieces.</note>SOme credible Persons passing 0536 0208 V upon the <hi>Thames</hi> about eight of the clock at night, <hi>March</hi> 21. 1660. beheld in the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens a fiery Meteor as big as a Man, which in a short time brake into many hundred of large Sparkles of Fire, and seemed to them to be Lights in the Sky shaped like Pyramids, sharp at the top and sqare at the bottom.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="46" type="section">
                  <head>XLV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Strange appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritions in the Heavens seen by many at <hi>London</hi> bridge, <hi>Mar.</hi> 0536 0 21. 1660.</note>UPon the 21. of <hi>March</hi> 1660. between 7 and 8 of the clock 0536 in the evening, was seen in the Air at <hi>London-bridg</hi> by very many judicious &amp; sober Citizens, full West, or West by North, several Forms and Figures variously metamorphosed, being the perfect shapes and representations of several Beasts, One Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, sundry Men, and two Armies. The Relation take as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, as it was drawn up by several of the Spectators, who immediately while the thing was yet fresh in their minds, went together, and every one contributing his Observations, they agreed unanimously upon the ensuing Description.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 There appeared the figure of a great Cathedral with a high Tower or Steeple advancing it self in the middle of it, which after a short continuance vanished.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 There was represented the form of an Oak with very large arms and spreading boughes, which also vanished after a short season.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The third figure was a very large Mountain, of which the Pyramid or lesser part stood downward, being placed between the said Cathedral and the Oak, which remained fixed for the space of a quarter of an hour without any variation at all; And after that these five several forms of Beasts of Prey seemed to issue from the right hand, or North part thereof, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 The first whereof was in the form of a devouring Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codile coming out of the middle of the Altitude of the said Mountain, and downward with the mouth wide open, which after a short space changed it self.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Into the form of a furious Bull, which was in a short time Metamorphosed. And in the</p>
                  <p n="3">3 Third place represented it self in the form of a fierce Lyon Rampant which was also suddenly. And in the</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Place altered into the figure of a perfect Bear, which was immediately turned. And in the</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:152943:17"/>5. Place into a Swine or Bore; And so there were the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentations of a devouring Crocodile, a furious Bull a fierce Rampant Lyon, and a beastly Bore or a Swine which alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately issued out of this great Mountain, which so stood or rose up between the said Cathedral and the Oak, all which eight apparitions being quite vanished, the same Mountain see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med suddenly to rend and divide it self from the top, but great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est part thereof into two distinct parts, which again were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately formed into 2 very beasts fastned or chained toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the hinder parts, the one seeming to draw one way, and the other drawing the quite contrary way, <hi>viz.</hi> That on the left hand which faced and drew towards the South, resem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled an Elephant with a Castle on his back.</p>
                  <p>That on the right hand towards the North, seemed to be a Lion or most like unto a Lion to all the beholders, but none could so clearly discern what this tenth figure was as they did the rest; But it stood on the right hand with its head Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly, and seemed with all its might to draw the Elephant that way, But suddenly after the Castle on the Elephants back va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished, the Elephant himself loosing his shape.</p>
                  <p>And then in the very position or station where the Castle stood (as near as we could judge) we clearly observed about 5 or 6 Men rise up, which during their continuance were in an uninterrupted Agitation and perplexed motion to and fro, backwards and forwards.</p>
                  <p>After this the other of those two Beasts which were fastned together and seemed to look and draw North and South as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid <hi>(viz.)</hi> That on the right hand in the form of or most resembling a Lion, was of a sudden and in a moment wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully transformed into the shape of a Horse with a Rider upon his back; but both suddenly seem to fall downwards; and so</p>
                  <p>There arose another Cloud which in a short time formed it self into the perfect resemblance or lively figure of the head of a Whale, having his mouth also wide open. And then</p>
                  <p>There appeared on the right hand at a further distance North-west or N. W. and by N. Another Cloud which represented it self to our view in the perfect form of a great head with a Cap thereupon, in the perfect form of a Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal's Cap as the same are usually pictured, having two horns of a very considerable length affixed therunto, And between the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152943:17"/>said Whales head and the said other head or Cap which had the said large Horns, there were again a few men more seen, moving up and down with a very swift motion; But all these men also suddenly disappeared, one onely excepted continued but a little longer then the rest moving up and down in much Majesty, magnificence and state. And then</p>
                  <p>There arose another great confused Cloud near unto the said great Head and Cardinals Cap, which had the two large Horns, but something more Northerly, which Cloud after a little time seemed like unto some large ruinous structure or building seen at a great distance, but while the beholders were looking wistly tkereupon, the same then peefectly appeared to be a formidable Army or body of men set in Battalia which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced Southward. And then</p>
                  <p>There arose another Cloud on the left hand towards the South leaving that single Magistick person a little more Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly, which Cloud formed it self into an Army, which was lesse then the first or Northern Army; This Southern or lesse Army advanced it self, with much seeming Celerity and speed against the said greater Northern Army, and being come near each other, the said single Magistick person vanished, and by or about the time he was totally extinct; Then both Armies seemed furiously to encounter and assail each other, and after the fierce on-set or charge, both Armies seemed to retreat a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and then as formerly they made a second furious charge, during which time although the front of the Southern Army stood stoutly to it and seemed to get ground of the Northern main body, and made them seem a little to retrait, yet the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rair of the Southern Army seemed to be discomposedly confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, and by degrees totally extinct whereupon the said Northern Army made a third and furious Charge against the Front or remainders of the Southern Army, and they against the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Army; and being so engaged both Armies seemed a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to retreat, so as an interval was seen between them; And then without any discernable victory obtained by either party, the heads of the men of the said Armies which before were clearly discernable, became a confused Cloud or Chaos and so vanished away both together; But the whole duration of all these three fierce Fights, Conflicts, Combates or Battles were very short and transcient, and continued not in the whole for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152943:18"/>above half a quarter of an hour, and then all seemed to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend into the great Horizon Clouds, so far forth as these Spec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators could or did then and there observe that night save only that in the last place.</p>
                  <p>The First and longest whereof seemed to be fixed to the middle part of some houses or building near Charingcross.</p>
                  <p>The Second longest or middlemost seemed likewise to be burning about the middle part of some houses in the Strand.</p>
                  <p>The last and shortest seemed likewise to the burning as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said upon some houses or buildings either on or about, or between the Temple and Fleet-bridge.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="47" type="section">
                  <head>XLVI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Two Moons seen at <hi>Chis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick April</hi> 12. 1661.</note>
                     <hi>APrill</hi> the Twelfth 0163 0146 V 1661. about one of the Clock in the Morning were seen at <hi>Chiswick</hi> in the County of <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sex</hi> two Moones, some of the Spectators did assure an honest Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen of <hi>London</hi> of the Truth thereof from whose mouth we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this information.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Two Moones were seen at</hi> Dubling <hi>in</hi> Ireland, October 11. 1342. <hi>and not many Monthes after that,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel.</note>
                     <hi>people endured most grievous Oppressions by the meanes of the Lord</hi> Ralph Ufford <hi>who came into</hi> Ireland <hi>as Lord chief Justice, concerning whom we read in Histories that none of his Predecessours were compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to him, he was a great Oppressour of the people, a Robber of the Goods both of Clergy and Laity, and much more to the same purpose sayes Mr.</hi> Cambden <hi>in his Annals of</hi> Ireland, <hi>page</hi> 188, 189.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="48" type="section">
                  <head>XLVII.</head>
                  <p>IN the Month of <hi>Aprill.</hi> 1661. about four or five of the clock 0163 0146 V in the Evening,<note place="margin">Four Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bows seen near <hi>Aulton</hi> in <hi>Hampishire.</hi>
                     </note> after a great storm of Rain and Hail, were seen by several credible persons near <hi>Aultan</hi> in <hi>Hampshire,</hi> four perfect Rain-bows standing directly over each other, and a little distance between every one of them; The two lower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most were not altogether so large, neither did they extend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves so far as the other two did; This Information we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from an eminent Citizen of <hi>London</hi> who was then in the Countrey upon some occasions, and was an Eye-witness thereof.</p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:152943:18"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>At</hi> Wien <hi>in</hi> Austria <hi>in the same Month of</hi> April Anno 1619. <hi>There appeared three</hi> Rain-bows <hi>in the Heavens,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel.</note>
                     <hi>and in the same year,</hi> October 25. <hi>a great and bloody Fight was fought at the</hi> Donaw-bridge <hi>in the same Town of</hi> Wien <hi>betwixt the</hi> Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemians <hi>and General</hi> Bucquoy, <hi>in which Encounter were slain on the Imperial side,</hi> 4500 &amp;c. <hi>As you may see at large in the</hi> Germ. Prod. <hi>p.</hi> 9.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="49" type="section">
                  <head>XLVIII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Ten Rainbows and four half ones seen near <hi>North-allerton</hi> in 0163 0 <hi>Yorkshire.</hi>
                     </note>WE have also an account of several Rain-bows that were 0163 01 lately seen together by divers persons at <hi>Northallerton</hi> in <hi>Yorkshire,</hi> the true and full Relation, whereof take as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, being an extract of a Letter from a Gentleman of very good quality in those parts to an eminent Citizen of <hi>London.</hi> I understand that divers persons between eleven and twelve of the clock on that great windy night, saw at <hi>North-allerton</hi> ten Rain bows, and four or five half ones; they stood all one way and together, there being about a yard distance between each of them. My Informer who with divers others saw this thing is a credible person, and yet at my House, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="50" type="section">
                  <head>XLIX.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A great Pillar of Fire seen at <hi>Bednol Green, April</hi> 23. 1661.</note>UPon the 23. 0163 0146 V of <hi>Aprill,</hi> 1661. (the day of his Majesties In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auguration) about the time of that dreadful storm of Thunder and Lightning, there was seen in the Sky at <hi>Bednall-Green</hi> near <hi>London,</hi> a great Pillar of Fire, and there seemed to encompasse it burning Coles of Fire, it continued a lit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le space of time, and then vanished. The Relation comes from some of the Eye-witnesses, persons of Credit and Inhabitants there.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="51" type="section">
                  <head>L.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Fiery Clouds and Meteors seen at <hi>Picka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dilla, Aprill</hi> 23. 1661.</note>THe same 0163 0146 night also about ten of the clock, were seen by se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral persons near <hi>Pickadilla,</hi> strange fiery Clouds and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teors very terrible to the Spectators; from some of whose Mouths we Received the Information.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="52" type="section">
                  <head>LI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Three Suns seen near <hi>Kingston, May</hi> 14. 1661.</note>UPon Tuesday <hi>May</hi> 0163 0146 14. 1661. from the hours of five till seuen in the Morning, were seen three <hi>Suns</hi> by several per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons near <hi>Kingston</hi> upon the <hi>Thames;</hi> the one appeared Easterly a little distance from the true Sun, and was of a blood colour,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152943:19"/>the other more Southerly, and was half of a blood and half of a Silver colour, All three were of equal magnitude and equal distance from each other; some of the Spectators do affirm, that when they first appeared, their position was Triangular; But afterwards they stood in a direct line, and as the true Sun a rose in its splendour, the other two by degrees disappeared; The whole Relation comes from sober discreet persons Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witnesses.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Paralel.</note>
                     <hi>There appeared three</hi> Suns <hi>in the Heavens not long before that contention happened between</hi> Galba, Otho <hi>and</hi> Vitellius <hi>about the Roman Empire.</hi> Clark<hi>'s Prod.</hi> p. 484.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Also in the year</hi> 53. <hi>three</hi> Suns <hi>were seen at</hi> Rome <hi>upon which a great Famine did immediately ensue.</hi> Lycost. <hi>p.</hi> 247.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The like also appeared in</hi> Germany Anno 1541. <hi>about which time</hi> Popery <hi>was rejected in the Palatinate.</hi> Signum Coelest. <hi>p.</hi> 5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The same</hi> Prodigie <hi>was also seen near</hi> Brunswick Anno 1550. <hi>in which year great troubles did arise in</hi> Antwerp, <hi>the Inquisition opposed in the</hi> Netherlands, <hi>and several of the Princes E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors made War against the Emperour.</hi> Signum Coelest. <hi>page</hi> 5. 6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the time of the</hi> German <hi>Wars three</hi> Suns <hi>were frequently seen, and there alwaies followed some bloody battle which was fought near those places; See</hi> Germ. Prod. <hi>p.</hi> 9. 11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The like also as many credible persons have affirmed, was seen in</hi> England <hi>on the</hi> 19. <hi>of</hi> November 1648. <hi>as also in the several years,</hi> 1639, 1644, 1645, 1646, 1647. <hi>And especially in the year</hi> 1650. <hi>Not long before that famous and bloody Fight be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Ʋs and the</hi> Scots <hi>at</hi> Dunbar.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="53" type="section">
                  <head>LII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A dreadful whirl-wind accompanied with strange and prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the 0163 0 Heavens.</note>UPon the 24. of <hi>May</hi> 1661. there was about <hi>Market-street,</hi> 0163 and several other places adjacent, in the Counties of <hi>Hertford, Bucks</hi> and <hi>Bedford,</hi> a dreadful whirle-wind ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with many strange and prodigious Apparitions in the Heavens, whereof many of the Inhabitants in those places were SPECTATORS, and the most sober and discreet that we can find out amongst them, have given us
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152943:19"/>the substance of the following description thereof.</p>
                  <p>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>veral persons of very good credit inhabitants of <hi>Kens<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> in the County of <hi>Hertford</hi> do inform us that upon the aforesaid 24 of <hi>May,</hi> 1661, in the fields of the said Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish of <hi>Kensworth,</hi> about two of the clock in the Afternoon they with divers o hers, heard a very dreadfull and strange noise in the <hi>Air,</hi> which they could not te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l what to liken to, some conceived it was like a continued noise of Thunder, at some distance, others compared it to the noise of severall drums beating together; immediately after this frightfull noise, there arose a very strong and tempestuous wind, and with that a black dark Cloud with a great smoak appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and above the cloud and the smoak they beheld very clearly the form of two May-poles, the one of a dark, and the other of a whitish colour, they were so plainly visible that the ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y children (who were at the same time gatheri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g stones in the field) took great notice of them, and were able to describe them. The Spectators had a ful view of these May-poles, as they passed along in the Air, for the space of half a mile, u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>till they saw the whiter May-Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e wholly to vanish, and the other to loose very much of it's shape and fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m; This noise and representations went along from <hi>Kensworth</hi> to the next Town called <hi>Caddington,</hi> and passing through a field of one <hi>Thomas Birchmoors,</hi> where his Servants were then at Plow, the noise and Representati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons aforesaid, were so dreadful and they so affrighted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, that immediately with great amazement, they ran a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from their work, and left their horses in the field. The wind was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o viol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt that it took up stones in great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, both in the aforesaid field, and else-where, and threw them up a very great height into the Air, from this field in passed to great House, called <hi>Caddington Berry</hi> belonging to the Dean of <hi>Pauls;</hi> where a Court was kept for him at that same time, and the Cook who did dresse the dinner there that day going forth upon some occasions had been carried away by the Whirlwind, but that he took hold of something and so stayed himself as he hath since confessed: It also took off many Tyles from the said house, and a great
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152943:20"/>deal of thatch from the Barns and out-houses, it threw up the water out of a Pond there, as if (according to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of some of the Spectators) a thousand men had been lading of it with shov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ls, not far from hence it tore up di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers trees by the roots, and did bow down severall very tall Spires, that the tops of them did very near touch the ground and in one place a Barn consisting of three b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y of building, was taken up from the ground-pinning and turned quite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
                  <p>And as it passed from <hi>Caddington-Berry</hi> it caried along with it as it were sheets of dirt, water and stones which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> took up in the air, and were plainly descorned by the Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators.</p>
                  <p>We have yet a further account of this strange Prodigie as it was seen by other persons in other places which you may take as followeth.</p>
                  <p>Two very discreet and sober men living near <hi>Dunstable,</hi> do assure us that they 2 being together on the said 24. of May, did see between <hi>Dunstable</hi> and <hi>Marketstreet,</hi> a very dark and black cloud passing towards <hi>Caddington,</hi> out of which there issued according to their apprehensions, a Sword, with the point hanging downwards, which grew bigger and bigger, till it came to the exact form of a Steepl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with the bottome upwards, which was very dark and black but the Spire (which as we said was next the earth, and as near as the beholders could judg in the middle of the cloud) was of a brighter colour, and did very much extend it selfe downwards towards the Earth: But after a while it drew it self up again much like to the figure of a Steeple as before and then within a short space of time it was so abreviated that it did not seem to them to be more then a Pole long and when it came to that Proportion the motion of it was very tremulous, so that it seemed to shake to and fro, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually. After this it extended it self downwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ds again, and appeared in the form and shape of a very tall Steeple, the lower end whereof did suddenly lessen to a very sharp point and quickly became perfectly taper, and then ascended up into the cloud, just like the smoak of a Chimny, and when
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152943:20"/>the smoak was vanished they saw the shape of the Steeple again, but it did soon shorten it self till it came to be about a Pole long, and then the lower end of it did shake as before, and at the upper end of it next the cloud appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a white streak, exceeding bright, and as near as they could judge about a foot and half long, and presently after all did center in the cloud again: immediately upon which the cloud divided, and one Part of it with an incredible swiftnesse did fly away from the other; This division of the cloud, was much about the place where they saw the Steeple before: That other part of the cloud which remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned was suddenly formed into the likeness of a Mil-wheel with Cogs, and did turn round with a very swift motion, upon which there seemed to fall down dead men, spreading their A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ms and legs, others as if they had been cut off at the waste, to their apprehensions, also there fell the quarters of mens bodies, as l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kewise the shape of mens bodies, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the shape of dogs, after which all became a very white cloud, and then it's motion wholly ceased. This whole Apparition was with great deliberation drawn up by the persons themselves who saw it, and by them presented to a person of known integrity in their Neighbourhood (who is also a contributer to this collection) from whom immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately we received it.</p>
                  <p>By two very sober credible persons we are informed, that upon the same 24. of <hi>May,</hi> they saw in the Air near <hi>Gaddes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den in the County of Hertford</hi> the form of a very high Steeple which as they apprehended it, did shake exceedingly, and by degrees it lessened it self to the Proportion of a May-p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le, and for a while continued in that shape, till at last it became like to a mans thigh with the leg and foot, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so with the knee bending, after a short space it disappea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
                  <p>Also upon the same day near <hi>Leighton Buzzard</hi> in the County of <hi>Bedford</hi> severall honest persons did see in the Air, the likeness of a May-pole, sometimes very straight, and sometimes very crooked twisting like a worm: This they behold for the space of halfe an hour, then there arose a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152943:21"/>smoak, and from the smoak issued the appearance of fire, which suddenly seized upon and consumed the <hi>May</hi>-pole.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="54" type="section">
                  <head>LIV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Seven Suns seen at <hi>Dentz.</hi> bout the 30 <hi>Feb</hi> 1660</note>THe <hi>Dutch Curranto</hi> doth tell us of many strange Prodigies that have this year been seen in divers places be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas; But because we have no other confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the truth of those reports we omit here to insert them, and shal only give the Reader an Account of the seven sons that were seen at <hi>Dantzick,</hi> about <hi>Frebruary</hi> last, as it at large Related in the following extinct of a Letter writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from thence by a Person of Quality and ingenuity to a M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rcha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t of good note in this City.</p>
                  <p>At <hi>Dentz. Feb.</hi> 20. 1660. <hi>No. Sti.</hi> about 11 of the clock when the Sun was going into the South East, &amp; the Air was very clear and still round about, <hi>I</hi> did see seven Suns toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther very destinctly in the Heavens, to wit, 3. coloured ones and 3 white ones besides the true Sun itself, about which was first a pretty big a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d almost closed circle round about, very fair of colours much like a Rain-bow, upon which on both sides 2. coloured Suns with the right Sun of the same altitude from the Horizon were sound both of them having long, clear and somewhat whitish tails, picket as a Comtt, the one bending towards the East, and the other towards the West. Secondly above the Circle right, over half the Sun under a ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ticle Line there stood a place of an inverted Circle o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Rain-bow very fair of all manner of colours, with another somewhat darkish collaterall Sun. Thirdly there presented it self yet a great circle of all manner of colou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s round about the Sun which co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>passed the fame c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> was somewhat palet and not altogether shut the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon being too near, and the Dia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eter of the circle being too great, upon which upon the top of the Capital Point there was also to be seen an invert piece of a Rain-bow ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bright and of Orient colours. Fourthly there came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother exceeding great and whitish silver col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ured circle, as it were ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of both the Collateral Suns, besides the true Sunne there came out of it (which encompassed the whole
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152943:21"/>Horizon, and stood equally from the same at the same di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, some twenty Degrees upon the Circle) three silver coloured Suns, the one in the North, towards the West, to wit over against the right Sun, the other in the East by North, and the 3 in the West, towards the South: through these 2 last, to wit, towrads the Easterly and Westerly pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed a white piece in circle-wise, comming from above and passing through the great bow on which they stood; so that through both these collaterall Suns there seemed to pass a white Crosse which was very notable and wonderfull to behold; neer an hour and half till all vanished again; So that the whole Phenomenon presented it selfe above me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure, or exceeding fair, besides its very remarkable, that 7 Suns after this manner truly have scarce ever been observed to have shown themselves together; Yea if <hi>I</hi> had Somwhat sooner observ'd the Phenomenon that might have been seen nine Sons together, for I could well discern the foot-steps of two more.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Paralell.</note>
                     <hi>Five Suns were seen in</hi> England <hi>in the</hi> 17. <hi>year of</hi> Henry <hi>the Third, after which followed so great a Darth, that many People were constrained to eat Horse-flesh and barks of trees, and in</hi> London <hi>twenty Thousand were star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for want of food.</hi> Baker, Chron. <hi>p.</hi> 100.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Strange Accidents, Storms, Earth quakes and other Prodigies happening on the Earth, from May <hi>1660.</hi> to the latter end of May <hi>1661.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">One seen on hors-back with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a head and two A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mies one of gray Coats, &amp; the other of red▪ Coats engaging one against the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> other.</note>BY a Letter from a very credible person in <hi>York-shire</hi> to a Citizen of note in <hi>London,</hi> it is certified that in the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nth of <hi>May,</hi> 1660. there was the apparition of one clad in white, on horse-back without a head, gallopping ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hedges and ditches, as in plain ways, immediately upon this there was the appearance of an Army of Gray co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ts driv ng a f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ock of sheep towards a hedge, where they did hack and cut them as they pas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d through some gaps in the hedge, upon which an Army of Red-Coats fell upon the Gray-Coats and totally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>outed them, and then the whole disappeared.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:152943:22"/>
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A</hi> Lyonness b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ught forth 3 Lyons. <hi>Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Plin. Nat. Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>Cap.</hi> 16. <hi>p.</hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>01.</note>IN or about the moneth of <hi>July,</hi> 1660. a Lyoness in the Tower of <hi>London</hi> brought forth three Lyon whelps at a time, a birth very rarely heard of except in some Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es at her first Litter; But in these parts of the World never known before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Hail-stones as big as Walnuts, accompaned with thunder and lightning.</note>
                     <hi>AT</hi> Dover August. <hi>4. 1660 from 10. of the Clock at night to two the next morning were such storms of Hail ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with Tirander and Lightning as the like was never known in those parte before, some of the Hailstones that fell were as big as walnets, some that were measured were four inches about, fifty pounds damage as least was done to Glass windows in that Town by this storm.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel.</note>Many such storms as this happened in the time of King <hi>John,</hi> but one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the rest was very remarkable wherein it hailed stones a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> big as Goose-egs, <hi>Baker. Chron. p. 82.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What sad miseries did hereupon ensue to the whole Kingdom all our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick stories do sufficiently testifie how were the people, yea the very Lords themselves harrased by cruel oppressions and illegal exactions, but above all it is unspeakable what the whole Nation suffered by continual broyls and Divisions,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Baker. Chron</hi> of the reign of King <hi>Iohn</hi> p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0.</note> both whiles Prince <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hur</hi> King <hi>Johns</hi> Nephew lived, who was his Competitor for the Crown, and also after his death from the <hi>Breach</hi> King and others; Insomuch that a good Historian sayes that the Kingdom was made the Stage of all miseries of rapine and cruelty; Two Armies in it on foot at once, each of them seeking to prey upon the other, and both of them upon the Countrey: Many other Parallels we could instance in, but that we are careful not to swell this Narative to too great a bulk; Only take these two short instances, the one in the year <hi>1496.</hi> at which time there were hail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stones <hi>18</hi> inches about, and not long after followed a gteat Plague especially in <hi>London, Baker. p. 268.</hi> The other is that in the last year of <hi>Queen Maries</hi> Keign, <hi>Anno. 1558.</hi> Hail-stones were taken up which being measured were <hi>15</hi> inches about, <hi>Baker Chron. p. 346.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>IV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A dreadful whirl-wind. <hi>Sep.</hi> 3. 1660. in <hi>Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cester-shire.</hi>
                     </note>UPon the third of <hi>September,</hi> 1660. in <hi>Leichester shire</hi> near the Town of <hi>Worthington</hi> began a very dreadful Whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind, it turned an house on one side, tore up a great Tree by the roots, casting it 4. or 5. yards from the place where it grew, it rent off the great limbs of an Apple-tree, and threw down a house into the street; the Chappel is sorely
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152943:22"/>shaken and the Chaunsel in danger of falling; Then it pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed on with great force and noise to <hi>Worthington</hi> Hall where it overturned five baies of Barn building and a Gate-house, It blew down a stack of chimnles, It hurried a man into the Orchard, where with his Arm he catched hold of a tree, and so stayed himself; From hence it passed renting trees and turning some up by the roots to a house that stands alone, where it took away a load of thorns, few of which could ever be found after, it took out also the side of another house at a town called <hi>Tounge,</hi> it overthrew a bay of Barn building, and rent a house where a woman with three children were miraculously preserved, to this house also it brought a great log of wood, none knows from whence, between <hi>Worthington</hi> and <hi>Tounge</hi> it is concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that this wind hath rent off, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>and turned up by the roots twenty loads of wood, it carried away likewise a Hive of Bees which could not since be heard of; this whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind ran about three miles in length, and the effects of it were not seen above twenty yards in breadth, some say that flames of fire were seen in it, This Relation comes from an honest discreet person, a spectator of the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned effects of this dreadful whirlwind.</p>
                  <p>Anno 1624 <hi>and</hi> May 8. <hi>The like to this happened in</hi> Ratisbone <hi>which tore up trees by the roots, and in a moment drave them to divers places, it threw down many houses in the City and Suburbs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>This Town after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards was streightly besieged and several times assaulted by the Imperial and</hi> Ravarian <hi>Army consisting of</hi> 45000. <hi>horse and foot, of whom at least</hi> 8000. <hi>were killed in the Siege; but the City at last was surrendered to them upon Honourable Conditions, See</hi> Cerm. Prod p. 20.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Such a storm also happened within a mile of</hi> Nottingham, <hi>the</hi> 5 <hi>and the last year of</hi> Queen Maries <hi>Raign by which amongst other things the water and mud of the River</hi> Trent <hi>were taken up and carried a quarter of a mile and dashed against Trees, many of which were torn up by the roots and cast twelve score off, also a Childe was taksn out of a mans band and carried two spears length high, and then let fall</hi> 200. <hi>foot off, and so died of the fall,</hi> Baker Chron. p. 346.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>UPon the 28. of <hi>August,</hi> 1660. were seen in <hi>Beverly</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-place, and in several other places in the said
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152943:23"/>
                     <note place="margin">an innumerable company of frogs &amp; Toads reigned out of air at Hull August. 8 1660.</note> an innumerable company of little frogs and toads or both: The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eople knew not how they came there, they having never been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore so infested with those kind of C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>es, but by cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances they Collected they m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ght c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me out of the air, because they found severall of them upon their cloaths, which did hang on the hedges, many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lso did fall down to the ground from the tops of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es, This is certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Merchant of <hi>Hull</hi> who was that day at <hi>Beverly</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket and saw these frogs, and helpt as him<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elf relates to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy many hundreds of them while he remained there.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The like to this happened in</hi> Alfa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia, Anno 1349. Lycost p 604.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Paralel.</note>
                     <hi>In the same year Pope</hi> Paulus tertius <hi>died, and the next your after there were great stirs in</hi> Germany, <hi>the Empe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>our</hi> Charles <hi>the fifth was so prosecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and invironed by those who rose up against him, that he very hardly es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caped with his life by flight,</hi> Lycost. p. 61<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">An innumerable company of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders seen march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up one of the streets at <hi>Bury</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> Sep. 6 1660</note>AT St. <hi>Edmunds Bury in Suffolk, Sept.</hi> 6. 1660, in the middle of the Broadstreet, there were got together an innumerable company of Spiders of a reddish colour, the spectators judged them to be as many as would have filled a Peck. These spiders marched together, &amp; in a strange kinde of order from the place, where they were first discovered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards one Mr. <hi>Duncombs</hi> house a member of the late Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, and since Knighted; and as the people passed the streets, or came near the spiders to look upon so strange a sight, they would shun the people, and kept themselves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a body till they came to the said <hi>Duncombs</hi> house, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whose door there are two great Posts, there they staied, and many of them got under the door into the house, but the greatest part of them climbing up the Posts spun a v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry great web presently from the one post to the other, and then wrapt themselves in it in two very great parcels that hung down near to the ground, which the servants of the house at last perceiving, got dry straw and laid it under them, and putting fire to it by a suddain flame consumed the greatest part of them, the number of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se that remained were not at all considerable, All the use that the Gentleman made of this strange accident so far as we can learn, is only this, that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:152943:23"/>he belives they were sent to his house by some Witches.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>VII</head>
                  <p>THe same day were also seen a great sworm of flyes flying over the said Town of St. <hi>Edmunds Bury,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A</hi> great swarm of flyes seen fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over St Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds Bury</note> their multitude was so great that the Sky seemed to be darkned by them both these relations come from credible persons eye-witnes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, however the Truth of these things is notoriously known to the Generality of the Inhabitants in that Town.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>VIII</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A Crab tree covered with Blossoms in the Month of Octo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 1660</note>IN the County of <hi>Merrioneth</hi> in <hi>Northwales,</hi> in a field or close which did belong to Colonel <hi>John Jones</hi> who was executed at <hi>Charing-Cross, Oct.</hi> 17. 1660 Was seen by a Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of his going forth into the said field that morning or very near the time, a Crab-tree covered all over with blos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>somes, he was so astonished at it that he could not believe is was so till he came near to the Tree and cut of a bough of it, which he carried home with him and shewed to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily and divers of his Neighbours; severall other credible persons saw the Tree, and many Gentlemen that were near and heard of it, sent for boughs, which when they saw, they were convinced of the Truth of the report. This relation we received first by Letters from the aforesaid Tennant, and a further confirmation we have since had of it by some very credible persons Inhabitants there eye-witnesses, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to <hi>London</hi> did here attest it <hi>viva voce.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <head>IX</head>
                  <p>THe like also was seen on another Crabtree not far from the former which began to blossome on the said 17 of <hi>October,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">another Crab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tree begun to blossome at the same time.</note> and the next day was full of ripe blossomes like the other, but within four or five dayes they all saded and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered away; The information of this particular, also we have by letters from the persons themselves who were Spec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>X</head>
                  <p>IN the Month of <hi>November</hi> last, 1660 in some part of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk</hi> were such multitudes of meddow-mice,<note place="margin">Muny meddow-mice which did eat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the gress in some parts of Norfolk</note> that in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred Acrees together, one could hardly set down his foot without treading on them, they did eat up the roots of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152943:24"/>the grass, and in one Mr. <hi>Spelmans</hi> ground as himself confest they have spoiled him so much grass, as used to keep 130. fat Cattle, he feared also he should be damnified by them 300. l. in a field of Cole-seed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Paralell.</note>
                     <hi>We finde that in the same month of</hi> Novemb. Anno. 1580. <hi>at</hi> Sou h-Minster. <hi>in</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nsey <hi>hundred in</hi> Essex, <hi>there appeared an infiinte number of Mice which over-whelmed the whole Earth in those Marches, and did shere and gnaw the grass to the roots, upon it followed a great murrein of</hi> Cattle <hi>which asterasards fed in those grounds, S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ow.</hi> Chron p. 689.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The year following</hi> Queen Elizabeth <hi>was much disturbed with</hi> Jesuits <hi>of which severall were executed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>XI</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A</hi> great tempe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> caused the Sea, it being a Spring tide to break down ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny strong banks in <hi>Cheshire</hi> to to the ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y great detriment of the Country.</note>IN <hi>Cheshire▪</hi> upon the 8. of <hi>Novem.</hi> last was a most Tempestu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wind, and it being a Spring tide, all the low grounds to <hi>Thornton Moore Arme</hi> were overflowed like a Sea; Great prejudice was done to many peoples houses, some Barns and Winmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s were blown down, the sea was so out-ragious and high that it broke down Cops at <hi>Jnce,</hi> that had stood as is reported 100 years, it brake down also a new strong Cops about green <hi>Warth</hi> which cost 3 or 400. l. makeing It break down <hi>Infrente Dams.</hi> which kept the flood from the Mill, and very much Corn in the mill was spoiled: The Sea also flowed over <hi>Jnce</hi> at <hi>Eldon-Marsh,</hi> and did very great harm in <hi>Frodsome-Marsh,</hi> many sheep and rabbets were drowned, as also beyond <hi>Chester</hi> many Sheep with Mares and Colts were drowned, very great harme was also done by Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack at Sea, few or no Vessels in those parts escaped; But that the Lord might make it eminently to appear that he Commands the Winds and the Seas, that they must obey him; It is credibly reported that in this great storme, two Children the one of ten the other seaven years of age, being playing together in a Cock-boat in <hi>Ireland</hi> were driven to Sea, and by the violence of the storm were brought to the <hi>English</hi> coast, and were both found in the Cock-bote en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded in each others Arms being almost dead, but when they were taken out of the Boat, such means were used that it pleased the Lord both of them recovered again; This whole relation we have by letters from very credible persons in those parts who do assure us of the truth of every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular hereof.</p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:152943:24"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the year</hi> 1534. <hi>such an inundation happened in</hi> Poland, <hi>and the same year the King of</hi> Scandia <hi>died- and</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> 8. <hi>King of</hi> England <hi>by act of Parliament abolished the Popes Authority in this Nation,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Para<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ell</note> Lycost. Pag. 555.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Also in the year</hi> 1568. <hi>Through the excessive swelling of the Sea, many places in</hi> Ze<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>and, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lland; <hi>and almost all</hi> Frizland <hi>were overflowed with Water. whereby besides the loss of many mens lives, the Country in other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cts was exceedingly damnified,</hi> Clarks Prod. p. 491. <hi>About that time great troubles were in those parts, because of the cruell and bloody p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rsecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Protestants in that Country by Duke</hi> de Alva, <hi>who for the tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous violence of some few in throwing down Images,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Did by death and i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>prisonments most unhumanely chastise all the rest of the party who were no wayes guilty of any crime, but such violent and unjust proceedings did quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly afterwards irritate the people to throw off the Yoke of the King of</hi> Spain, <hi>and there with the Idolatry and Superstition of</hi> Rome, <hi>whereby they rejoyced and so do to this day a very great freedom both in their civill and Religious capacities,</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Devil in the likenesse of a Bishop appeared to a Bishop appeared to a Scholar in <hi>Magdalen Coll. Nov.</hi> 10. 1660.</note>BY a letter from a very good hand from <hi>Magdalen</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg in <hi>Oxford</hi> it is certified that about the 10 of <hi>Nov.</hi> last, 1660 a Spectrum appeared to one <hi>Allen</hi> of that Colledg, which according to his own Relation was as followeth, he heard in the night when he was in bed, a noise like the noise of geese▪ he arose from his bed and looked out of his Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow which opened over the Bridg but saw nothing, but go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his bed again he saw a man as it were grovelling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the door, in his Pontificalibus, attired like a Bishop in his Lawen sleeves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>At first he was not much affrighted. but called to it and abjured it to speak, the Bishop immediately rose up and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached towards his bed, at which the young man was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ngly terrified, and crying out murder, murder, it vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, he since sayes, that he saw and heard something which he will discover to none; upon the report of this strang ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rition in the Colledg, the next night five or six schollars watched in that Chamber, and about midnight, on a sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain the candles went out, and immediately upon it was heard a great noise as of Children crying out, which so af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frighted them, that they all ran out of the Chamber; This is a thing generally known and talk't of by the Students in that house; though as it is reported the subpresident did his uttermost to suppress the rumour of it, and by his means
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152943:25"/>hath so awed the Scholar, that except it be to some special confidents he dares not own this to any.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel.</note>
                     <hi>An Apparition not unlike to this we find to be in the year</hi> 1403 <hi>in the Rain of</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> 4. <hi>when the Devil appeared in the likeness of a Gray or White Fryer at</hi> Danebury <hi>in</hi> Essex, <hi>he came into the Church and extreamly affrighted the people who were there assembled together, and great hurt was done to the Chancel and Steeple by him; For long after, several of these gray or white Fryers were hanged and beheaded for Treason, and many P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iories with their Passions were resumed and seized into the Kings hand,</hi> see Stow. Chron. p. 327.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A violent storm with thunder and lightning, wherein several persons were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>illed.</note>UPon the 23 of <hi>November</hi> last, 1660. there happened in <hi>Garnsey</hi> a most violent storm with terrible Thunder and Lightning wherein several persons were killed, and much hurt done otherwayes; of this the Publick Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencer gives a full and true Account, unto whom we refer the Reader.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="section">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A dreadful storm of wind in <hi>Yorkshire.</hi>
                     </note>UPon the 8 of <hi>December</hi> 1660 at night there happened, especially in <hi>York-shire</hi> and other parts Northerly, a very dreadful storm of winde, the like they say was never in any mans memory known before, very much hurt was done by the blowing down of chimneys and houses, but especially the Windmils and the ships went to wrack, it spared not the consecrated places, many Churches were sorely shaken the great Cathedral at <hi>York</hi> was damnified by it as it was judged at least 1500 <hi>l.</hi> neither did <hi>Rippon,</hi> nor <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verly</hi> Ministers escape free; The prejudice that the violence of this wind to several Towns is not to be valued. At the same time the Assurance Frigot designed for <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yny</hi> was sunk in the <hi>Thames</hi> and about 30 men drowned in her, the effects of this Storm also reached beyond the Seas; The Publick Intelligencer observes that upon the same day the house of Peers voted the digging up of <hi>Oliver Cromwels</hi> bones; The same day also was as great a Tempest in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and very much mischief done, some Stacks of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152943:25"/>Corn on my Lord <hi>Mazarines</hi> ground, were so blown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way and dispersed, that (as his Lordship related it) there was scarce a straw left upon a straw: some other great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices his Lordship with many other sustained in that Kingdome also,</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Paralel.</note>
                     <hi>At</hi> Brislaw <hi>in</hi> Silesia Anno 1625 <hi>there hapned a very great tempest which did very much mischief to the Churches, &amp;c. At the same place afterwards there were many hot and sharp encounters between the</hi> Imperialists <hi>and the</hi> Swedes <hi>as you may read at large in the</hi> Germane Prod. <hi>p.</hi> 25, 26.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Also upon the</hi> 9 <hi>of April</hi> 16: 8. <hi>near</hi> Hatford <hi>in</hi> Bark-shire, <hi>there hapned a very terrible tempest, and the same Summer,</hi> viz. August 23 <hi>following, the Duke of</hi> Buckingham <hi>was stabbed by L<seg rend="sup">t</seg>.</hi> John Felton, Stow. Chron. p. 1044.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We in this Island must never forget that Prodigious and dreadful storm of wind on the</hi> 4<seg rend="sup">th</seg>
                     <hi>of</hi> Novemb. 1637. <hi>About</hi> 10 <hi>of the Clock at night, which the famous and learned</hi> D<seg rend="sup">r</seg> Jackson <hi>Chaplain to his late Majesty in his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix to his Sermons on</hi> Luke 21.25. <hi>takes great notice of saying, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst all the forewarnining signs given to this Land as so many Summons to Repentance, none which have been within my memory did make so durable impressions upon my heart and thoughts as that late mighty wind,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Read more in the aforesaid Appendix: We all too well Remember what f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>llowed hereupon both in respect of the troubles in</hi> Scotland. <hi>and the civill wars a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst our selves for so many years together.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="section">
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A great Thunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in Oxford. <hi>Dec.</hi> 18. 1660.</note>A very great and terrible thunder and lightning hapned at Oxford Decemb. 18 which hath not been usuall in the winter season.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="section">
                  <head>XVI</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">a great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake in <hi>Leice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stershire</hi> Jan. 24. 1660.</note>UPon the 24 of <hi>January</hi> last 1660 between six and seven of the Clock at night there was a very great Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke in most most parts of <hi>Leicester-shire,</hi> and in some pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the adjacent Countries, it came at the first with a noise in the air like Thunder at a great distance, it shaked the houses very much, and in some places men could hardly stand except the held by something, it continued about the space a quarter of an hour: this is a thing Publickly known in most parts of that County as also in <hi>Rutland, &amp;c,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:152943:26"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel</note>
                     <hi>There was a dreadful Earthquake on the</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2 <hi>of</hi> October Anno 105. <hi>Not long after fellowed the most cruel and bloody persecution of the Christians under</hi> Trojan <hi>the Emperor</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the City of</hi> Lacedemon <hi>there happened also a very great Earthquake and not long after a certain people called</hi> Illotae <hi>which were their slaves rose</hi> up <hi>against them and put them to great distress,</hi> &amp;c. Plutarch de vita Cimonis p. 503.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>An Earthquake also happened in</hi> Constantinople Anno. 1509. <hi>After which ensued a great Plague whereby the City was for the most part un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peopled,</hi> Turk Hist. p. 476. <hi>And indeed according to the opinion of Philoso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>stilence in a natural way is the Common and ordinary effect of Earthquakes,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See many other Portanta of the Earthquakes in <hi>Trismeg. Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1. See <hi>Lycost de Prodig.</hi> p. 468.</note>
                     <hi>se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> Zanch de operibus Dei, p. 375. <hi>and so</hi> Seneca Quaest. <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> Cap. 27.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>On the</hi> 6 <hi>of</hi> April, <hi>and on the first day of</hi> May 1580 <hi>and the</hi> 22 <hi>year of the Raign of</hi> Queen Elizabeth <hi>there happened very great Earthquakes both in the City of</hi> London <hi>and several other places, in which years as we said before</hi> pag. <hi>The Pope sent aid to the</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ish <hi>who were in Rebellion against the Queen, but they were all by the blessing of God utterly defeated and cut off, See</hi> Stow. p. 687, 688,</p>
                  <p>Anno 1381. <hi>In the time of</hi> Richard <hi>the</hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>was a great Earthquake in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parts in this Nation, and what ensued thereupon you may read at large in</hi> Stow. Chron. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>83, &amp;c. <hi>See also</hi> Lycost. p. 468.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="section">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <p>UPon the 5 of <hi>November</hi> 1660 two great Hogs came two several and very strange unusual wayes up divers steps into the Cathedral of <hi>Canterbury,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Two Hogs come in <hi>the</hi> Cathedral at <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
                     </note> and went into the quire when the Prebends were in the midst of their Devotion, and there continued till they were driven out by the Vergers; The Generality of the Inhabitants of that City do very well remember that a little before the down-fall of the Hierarchy in the year 1641. The same thing happened in the same place, <hi>Malum Omen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="section">
                  <head>XVIII.</head>
                  <p>ABout the 26 of <hi>April</hi> 1661 at <hi>Spalding</hi> and <hi>Bourn</hi> and several other places in <hi>Lincolnshire</hi> it rained Wheat,<note place="margin">Wheat was rained. in <hi>Lincolnshire</hi> about <hi>April</hi> 26. 1661.</note> some grains of it were very thin and hollow, but others of a more condense substance, and would grinde into a fine flower, several Pecks of it were taken up out of Church leads, &amp; ot her houses that were leaded, several of the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants there who were eye-witnesses have brought up some of the grain to <hi>London,</hi> which some of us have seen, and as we are credibly informed a good quantity of it hath been presented to his Majesty by a person of honour.</p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:152943:26"/>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel.</note>
                     <hi>We find that</hi> Anno 722 <hi>in a field in</hi> Italy, <hi>there fell a great quantity of Corn from Heaven in a shower of rain: After which time, and in the same year</hi> Charles <hi>the Emperour did subdue the</hi> Saxons: <hi>And severall of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops were by the same Emperour for their pride and insolencies thrown out of their Bishopricks,</hi> Lycost. p. 328.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The like also happened</hi> Anno 828. <hi>In which year</hi> Ludovicus <hi>the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour transported an Army into</hi> Affrica, <hi>and in a pitched field did totally vanquish and overcome the</hi> Affricans, Lycost. p. 347, 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>About the year</hi> 1641 <hi>it rained a kind of grain in several parts of</hi> England <hi>which was like a withered wheat corn, but not so long, with a skin of dark colour, which being pulled off, the grain had a taste somewhat sharp and hot:</hi> Mr. Baxter <hi>assures us that he tasted some of it himself and kept som of it long, which fell on the lead▪ of the Ministers house in</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>idge North, <hi>where</hi> Mr Baxter <hi>then preached the Gospel, See</hi> Baxters <hi>Saints Rest.</hi> 8 <hi>Edition.</hi> p. 227.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="section">
                  <head>XIX.</head>
                  <p>IN the same Month of <hi>April</hi> 1660 about <hi>Chesterfield</hi> in <hi>Derbyshire</hi> it rained white ashes,<note place="margin">The raining of ashes near <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterfield</hi> in <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byshire.</hi>
                     </note> which fell in such quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities that several fields did look very white as if Snow had covered them; a person of very good credit, who hath late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been in those parts received this account from severall of the Spect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tors.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The like was seen at</hi> Constantinople, Anno 653. <hi>which did much terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the people, &amp; immediately there followed a great mortality by reason of the Pestilence which raged exceedingly in that City for many month<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> after,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Paralel.</note> Lyco. p. 322.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The same thing also happened near th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> same Place, Anno</hi> 74<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>being the year wherein</hi> Constantine <hi>took</hi> Constantinople <hi>by force,</hi> Lycost. pag. 329.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="section">
                  <head>XX.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A very fierce and suddain shower of rain in <hi>Lond. May</hi> 21 1661.</note>UPon the 21 of May, 1661 (the day before the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant was burned, there fell so much rain in <hi>Lond.</hi> by reason of a sudden showr which lasted not much more then half an hour) that most of the Streets were like Rivers, inso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that great Casks &amp;c. did swim down the streets: and in Coleman street the water was so high that a great dog could not passe the way but by swimming, whereof several Inhabitants there did take special notice: Near <hi>Smithfield</hi> also the water <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an with such violence that it bore down severall Hog-sties in the Castle-Inn-yard, and carried th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> down the common-shore to the middle of <hi>Cheek lane</hi> which is near 20 Rood, many thousand pounds as some Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions Citizens have affirmed will not make good the dammage which Merchants, Vintners, Victuallers, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152943:27"/>other Tradesemen have sustained by that hafty and violent showre.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The like storm of suddain rain happened in</hi> London <hi>the second year of</hi> King James,<note place="margin">The Paralell.</note> Anno. 1604. <hi>as you may read at large in</hi> Stow. Chron. p 844▪</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Also on the last of</hi> Septemb. 1558. <hi>and the fifth and last year of Queen</hi> Mary <hi>there was so great a shower that several boats were rowed from</hi> West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster Bridg <hi>into King-street,</hi> Bakers Chron. p, 347,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> like stood of waters to the space of half an hour the Clouds powered down upon</hi> Kutterberge <hi>in</hi> Bohemia. Anno. 1623. <hi>in the time of the bloody persecution which the Protestants did undergo there,</hi> See Bohem. Hist. p. 355.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="section">
                  <head>XXI</head>
                  <p>VVE must not passe by without observation the great and unusual rains that have fallen this Spring;<note place="margin">Great rain for many weeks to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether 1660.</note> The oldest man living can hardly remember the like, there being scarce a day or else a night for many weeks together wherein the Heavens did not pour down very great showers upon the Earth, the prejudices whereof we may justly fear (if the Lord in much mercy prevent not) the whole Nation will feel before this year be expired.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>These great rains are by our Historians numbred amongst the Casualties that happened in the time of that most unhappy King</hi> Henry the 6.<note place="margin">The Paralel.</note>
                     <hi>The troublesom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of whose Reign is sufficiently known to all that have been but ordinarily perfect in our English Chronicles and Histories.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Also in the year</hi> 1594. <hi>and the</hi> 36 <hi>of the Reign of</hi> Queen Elizabeth, <hi>it Rained from May till about the latter end of</hi> July <hi>almost every day or night, and after it followed (though a reasonablo good harvest) yet a great dearth of Corn and all manner of provisions, See Stow.</hi> p. 769.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="section">
                  <head>XXII</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">a woman delivè<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of a Monster in Scotland</note>BY divers letters from <hi>Scotland</hi> we are certified that a woman lately in that Nation brought forth a strange and dreadful Monster the description whereof take as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, being an extract of one of those letters which was sent from a known credible person in <hi>Scotland</hi> to a friend a near relation of his not far from <hi>London.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q>In the County of <hi>Bochanon</hi> in our Island, there was a Woman brought to bed of a certain Creature, which before it came forth was heard to squek, &amp; cry in the Womb, and as it was comming out, it did squek so terribly that every one run away affrighted, At last the Minister with several others came in, &amp; there was born a Creature all hairy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the girdle like a man Child, &amp; above the shouldiers two heads, on upon the top of the other, the upper like
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152943:27"/>the face of a Lion, and did immediately run up &amp; down the house, crying three times woe, woe, woe, to the world; The Father of this monster knoct it on the head, this is a certain truth,</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="section">
                  <head>XXIII</head>
                  <p>VVE have from very good hands assured of a very strang providence of God that lately happened at <hi>Wincan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> in the County of <hi>Sommerset</hi> on the 29 of <hi>May</hi> 1661. the Relation whereof as it was received from honest &amp; faithful persons eye—witnesses take as followeth.</p>
                  <p>Upon the said 29 of <hi>May</hi> (being his Majesties birth day, and appointed as a day of thanksgiving for his Majesties Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storation to the exercise of his regal power over these Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;) Mr. <hi>Sacheveril</hi> the Minister of the Town of <hi>Wincanton</hi> aforesaid did in the Celebrating the memorial of that day or on the Lords day foregoing, preach to the people from that portion of Scripture, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.25. <hi>But if ye shall do wickedly, ye shall be consumed both ye and your King:</hi> From which words he raised very clearly this observation, <hi>vizr That wicked and prophane men are the worst Subjects,</hi> which he demonstrated and confirmed by severall arguments, and in his application did endeavour to convince that part of his Authority which his Text was most appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable of the inconsistency of their present course of Prophanenesse, Drunkennesse, Whoredome, Scoffing at Religion, Swearing, Blaspheming, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With that which is Loyalty indeed &amp; wherewith any Prince can be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther advantaged or honoured; The rude debauched multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the Lown (who judged themselves the best Subjects because most obnoxious to the preachers reproofs) were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>x<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly scandalized and enraged at this Doctrine, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to be avenged on the Minister for so open detecting their disloyalty to their Soveraign, to which purpose they prepare an effigies made of straw and clothed it in black; which might represent Mr. <hi>Sacheveral</hi> and put into i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s hand, the Catechism compiled by the late reverend Assembly of Divines, and with a horse or horses d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ew it through the Town upon a Sled, and at several honest sober mens doors
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152943:28"/>as they passed along they made a stand, demanding of it whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it would read the common-prayer or no to which some were appointed still to make answer in the negative, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they drew it away to the place where they had set in order above an hundred fagots of furses &amp; other such like combustible matter in the midst of which pile they place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e aforesaid effiges upon a short pole, and then kindled their Bonefire; and though the effigies was in the midst of a very quick and fierce flame which ascended above it, yet the fire had no power at all over it, but it remained after a good part of the materials were consumed altogether untouched, at which the multitude was so enraged that one of them discharged a Gun at it, which as he shot it off, brake in pieces and hurt himself with some others that stood near him, Then another of the company struck at it with a hanger which also by the force of the blow brake in two, then they took it down and held it in the fire, and the winde blew the flame from it, so that they could not make it burn, then they held it in the fire on the contrary side, and the windo imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately turned &amp; kept the flame again from seizing upon it; After all they were forced to pull it to pieces, &amp; so by peace-meal at last consumed it in the fire; This relation with the several circumstances of it, as we have here inserted them will be attested by divers inhabitants in the said Town of <hi>Wincanton,</hi> and the truth of the story is so notoriously known there, that the actors themselves have not the face to deny it or any part of it. &amp; we cannot but hope that it hath left some convinction upon them, seeing the Lord by this strang and miraculous providence hath so publiquely &amp; manifestly disowned and tebucked their barbarous &amp; inhumane usage (and that only for telling them the truth) of their faithfull Minister in their attempts (though in vain) against that man of Straw which they made to represent him. And let it also be an encouragement to him. and all the rest of the Lords faithful Messengers in this day of great Apostacy to hold fast the truth and to cleave to that God <hi>who stilleth the noise of the Seas, the noise of their waves and the tumult of the people.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:152943:28"/>
               <head>Some remarkable Apparitions and Prodigies that have hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Waters together with strange and ununsual double Tides from May <hi>1660.</hi> to the <hi>14</hi> of Feb. <hi>1660.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <p>LEtters from a very credible person out of York-shire to one of q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ality in London do certifie us, that at Craven in York-shire was seen 6: Coach-horses drawing a Coach,<note place="margin">The lowest of 3. Springs dried up</note> firs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> down and then up the river with a great fiercenesse.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>II.</head>
                  <p>WIthin a mile of Fetcham in the way to Learher-head in Surrey were three springs, the lower of which used to run very strongly, but since the latter end of Octob. 1660 for a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>out four months it would not run at all, though the two uppermost Springs (which according to an ordinary custome in nature should first have falled) have continued all this while running. Some of the inhabitants near the place take great notice of it, because it nere in their remembrance hapned so before, except once which was in the year 1648. and much about the same time of the year.<note place="margin">A great Well dried up rear <hi>Chrick</hi> Town.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>ABout the beginning of Winter last, a very great Well by Chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k Town, four miles from Osweldstry in Denbigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire was also dried up; which the inhabitants there can remember at any time heretofore hapned, except a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the last great plague.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>IV<note place="margin">Two small streams broke forth</note>
                  </head>
                  <p>IT is very certain that this year both at <hi>Cradon</hi> in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Surrey,</hi> as also at a place called <hi>Fairemile</hi> near <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> opon <hi>Thames</hi> in the County of <hi>Oxford,</hi> a smal stream of water hath broken out, which the adjacent Inhabitants of both places do t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> norice of, with very great fear and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of Spirit, because when the like hath happened heretofore, cither Pestilence, Famine, or some dreadfull chance and revolution have alwayes ensued.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:152943:29"/>
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A</hi> double Tide at <hi>London-Bridge, Novemb. 2.</hi> 1660.</note>UPon the second of <hi>November</hi> last, being the day where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in her Majesty the Queen Mother came to <hi>White-Hall,</hi> there was a strange double Tide observed at <hi>London</hi> Bridge; the account whereof take as followeth: Whereas by the usual course of the River it should have ebbed till four of the Clock in the morning, and then should have flowed till eight or nine, but this morning, <hi>viz. November</hi> the second, it was flood from one of the clock till four, and then eb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed about two hours time a yard and a half, and then which was about six of the clock it was flood again till ten in the forenoon and then ebbed again.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Another strange tide whereby 1000. sheep were drowned near <hi>Grauesend.</hi>
                     </note>THere was likewise <hi>November</hi> 16. when there was no winde stirring, another very strange Tide at <hi>London-bridge,</hi> it should have ebbed that morning till four or five of the clock, and it was flood and flowed till four, and ebbed, about an hour or somewhat more, where common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ebbi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g is seven hours below Bridge; After that the water seemed to stand still, and run no way for an hour standing water, then it began to flow again, and though together, and the Ships did ride as if they had been in this happened but two dayes after the Moon entered into her last quarter, at whch time the Tides are alwaies low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est, yet it was as high as any Spring Tide whatsoever, it was observed to rise five foot at least higher then the Tide immediately foregoing, and it rose so high and that so suddenly and unexpectedly, that near <hi>Gravesend</hi> above 1000. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heep were drowned; This flood continued for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 3 hours and then abbed again.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the</hi> 17 <hi>year of</hi> Queen Elizabeth, <hi>there happened at</hi> London-Bridge <hi>a double Tide somewhat like those which we have mentioned in the second foregoing particulers,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel.</note> Baker Chron. p. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2. <hi>In the same year died</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w Parker <hi>the Arch Bishop of</hi> Cante bury, <hi>as also not long after</hi> VVal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voreux E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rle <hi>of</hi> Essex, <hi>and Earl Marshal of</hi> Ireland <hi>fell sick of a</hi> La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k <hi>and pres<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ntly died</hi> Stow. p. 679.681.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sach a Tide likewise happened in the year</hi> 1608. <hi>and not long after a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ace was concluded betwixt the King of</hi> Spain <hi>and the States General of the united P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ovinces,</hi> Stow p. 893.</p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:152943:29"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We find likewise that a little: before the late King</hi> Charls (<hi>then Prince of</hi> VVales) <hi>began his voyage towards</hi> Spain, Anno. 1622. <hi>The Thames shisted four Tides within the space of five hours</hi> Stow. p. 1035.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>A</hi> strange Tide St <hi>Hull.</hi>
                     </note>UPon the same day also, it is most certain that there w a very strange Tide at <hi>Hll,</hi> after it was fall'n water, and according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o its cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se should have bin half <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bb, it was flood again, and higher by a foot then at the time of high water, This comes from an honest discreet Merchant that lives there who was an eye-witness.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>UPon the 20 of <hi>November</hi> 1660 the River <hi>Derwent</hi> was it <hi>Derby,</hi> and five miles above and five miles below that Town,<note place="margin">The Riv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r <hi>Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went</hi> near <hi>Derby</hi> dried up, <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemb.</hi> 20. 1660.</note> for three or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r hours together totally dried up, so that no water during that time came to any of the Mille upon the River, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> boats were all on ground, and the fishes left upon the sand, so that the Children took them up in their hands, and in s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>veral places the people went over the Channel with their shoos dry shod. This is the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable because this River <hi>Derwent</hi> is in-land River, and useth not at any time to ebb and flow, and it is also at <hi>Derby</hi> above 100 foot broad and seven or eight soo tdeep at least,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Canden</hi> sayes of this River that it carries a full and lofty stream, <hi>Brit.</hi> p. 554.</note> and bes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s it is likewise an extraordinary quick fierce stream; Therefore the hand of the Lord is the more eminently seen in cutting off the waters thereof for so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miles together, and for so considerable a space of tmie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel.</note>Anno 1399 <hi>and the last year of King</hi> Richard <hi>the</hi> 2. <hi>his Raign, the River</hi> Ouse <hi>near</hi> Bedford <hi>stood still, and by reason that the waters gave back on b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th sides men might pass <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u foot within the very Channel for</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>miles to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, not without wondering of all that saw it,</hi> Cambd. Brit. p. 399.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What some did adjudge this to signifie you may see</hi> Biker Chron. p. 167. <hi>It was conceive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> also that it did portend the civil broyles between the Houses of</hi> York <hi>and</hi> Lancaster <hi>which happened not long after, and wherewith</hi> England <hi>for a long time was rent in pieces,</hi> Cambd. ibid.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Also in the year</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>43. <hi>and the</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>of the Raign of</hi> Henry <hi>the</hi> 6. <hi>The same River O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>se on new years day stood suddenly still, and divided it self. VVhat the thoughts of many then were of the signification of that wonder, and what not long after it did ensue, the indicious Reader may find at large in</hi> Baker Chron. p. 213.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:152943:30"/>
                  <head>IX</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WHereas upon the 16. of</hi> Decem. <hi>1660 it should have been full Sea at</hi> London-bridge,<note place="margin">The water so low at London-bridge that with a Pole one might have leapt over the Channel.</note>
                     <hi>according to the usuall course of the Tides at ten of the Clock in the morning and twelve minutes after; at the same time hour the Thames was so low that some walked on the sands into the middest of the River, and at six of the clock the same night, it was so dry to the very narow Channel that one with the help of a Pole might have lept over it, as some discreet persons eye-witnesses do affirm.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the year of <hi>1550</hi> when the Persecution began to wax hot in <hi>Scotland</hi> against the Professors of the Truth, amongst many Prodigious signs, which were then observed, this was one, that some great River in the midst of Winter were dried up, <hi>Sportes. wood, Hist.</hi> of the Church of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Also in the year <hi>1592</hi> the River of Thames was so low, that some did ride over it on both sides of <hi>London-Bridge,</hi> and shortly after the Pestilence brake forth with great violence, and swept a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way many families in <hi>Lond. Stow. p. 765, 766.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anno 1632</hi> a little before the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> was slain at that fatal battle of <hi>Lutzin,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">another strange ride at London-bridge, Feb. 1. 1660.</note> a River of no smal account in <hi>Swede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> lost its water, insomuch that for a whole day a man might go through it with a dry foot, <hi>Germ. Prod. p. 48.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>X</head>
                  <p>UPon the 14 day of Feb. 1660 there was likewise ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther very strange Tide at London-Bridge, for after a whole houre ebb as the least the flood cam in again, flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for an hour and half, and then for about the same space of time the water seemed to stand still, and then it ebbed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Strange and un-sual accidents, together wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> some remarkable Judgements befalling divers persons in this Nation, from <hi>June 1660</hi> to the <hi>23.</hi> of <hi>April. 1661.</hi>
               </head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>I.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>White</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister of <hi>Ruff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> struck dead while he was reading the Service book.</note>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Mr. <hi>White</hi> Ninister of <hi>Ruffham</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> a man of Parts and one that did pretend very much zeal for the Reformation of Religion in the Presbyterian way, upon the late change did write in vindication of Episcopacy, &amp;c.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152943:30"/>Or gave some such like Testimony of his receding from his former Principles, and was one of the first Ministers in those parts that attempted to read the Service-book: But it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the Lord to give him a very sharp rebuke, for upon his first attempt he was smit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en and fainted away while he was in the Reading-place, but coming presently to himself a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, he proceeded to read on, and was smitten in the like manner the second time, and so carried out of the Church for dead, though afterwards by the use of means his life re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to him again; but whether he hath since recovered his perfect health again or no we have not herad.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>II</head>
                  <p>UPon the 3 of <hi>June</hi> 1660 being the Lords day, at <hi>Broking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> in <hi>Glostershire,</hi> there was a Religious meeting of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny godly Christians from several Towns in those parts. The place of Scripture which the Preacher did that day treat up-was Jude 14, ver. 15. <hi>And Enoch also the seventh from Adam, Prophesied on these, saeying, Behold the Lord cometh with Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of his Saints to execute judgement upon all, and to convince all that were ungodly amongst them of all their ungod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y deeds which they have ungodly committed, and of all their hard spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which ungoly sinners have spoken against him,</hi> And while he was expounding and applying that Scripture, the Clark of the Town his Daughter (who was publickly noted to be a prophane &amp; malitious scoffer and reviler of all that desired to walk strictly at becometh the Gospall, and more particularly of these who were assembled as aforesaid, and (according to credible information) she was active in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing some of the County Troop to come and disturb them in their meeting that day) with her mother came in among them to scoff as at other times, but more especially to see these poor honest men routed and pulled out of their mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting-place by the Souldiers, who by this time for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose were even a the door. But a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>st remarkable and righteous hand of the Great and terrible God did after a most dreadful manner prevent her therein, for (having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued but a very little while) she gave a great and very sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dn in scriech and sell down dead before them all: her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152943:31"/>with divers that were near her, used all the means they could to restore her life, but all proved ineffectuall; This judgment of God hath been generally taken notice of in those parts, as a thing publiquely known to be true, and the effects of it hath been considerable in many persons there.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>III.</head>
                  <p>ONe Mr. <hi>Ourd</hi> formerly a Major in the late Kings Army, being present one Lords day, about the beginning of <hi>September</hi> 1660,<note place="margin">One offended with an honest Minister for speaking the Common-Pray-book as he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, prosecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster with great violence, but the Lord put a stop to it by ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away the proseutor by sudden death</note> st <hi>Anwick</hi> Church in Northumberland, where one Mr. <hi>Rowell</hi> is Minister, and hearing him that morning preach something as he conceived against the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer Book, expressed great discontent at is, and in the afternoon caused the Church doors to be shut up, so that Mr. <hi>Rowell</hi> was constrained to Preach to the People in the Church-yard: he also threatned that the Minister should forthwith be turned out of his living: In order whereunto he not long after repaired to the Assizes at New-Castle, and there indicted the said Mr. <hi>Rowell</hi> for speaking disgracefully of the Common-Prayer Book, but by the interposition of some friends of the Ministers he was wholly prevented of ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting his design for that time: but being in pain to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered of the mischeief he intended this good man, he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the Judges at <hi>Durham</hi> Assizes also, and there his suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess was better then at <hi>Newcastle,</hi> for he procures something wherewith he purposes severely to scourge Mr. <hi>Rowel:</hi> but now the Lord immediately from Heaven pleads the cause of his faithful innocent Servant, &amp; makes his Prosecuter a sad and publick example of his displeasure; for as he was returning from <hi>Durham</hi> to <hi>Anwick</hi> 24 of Sept. 1660. And going over a shallow water not a foot deep he fell suddenly from his horse, some that were near and saw him fall, made all possible hast to him, who when they came to help him up (as they themselves relate) found him dead and very cold, they used what means they could to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t in vain, When the Jury viewed his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, they gave in their verdict that he was dead before he
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152943:31"/>fell from his horse, for they could find no hurt at all about him which they could judge was occasioned by his fall that might bring him to his end; This is a thing too notoriously known in those parts to be questioned.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel.</note>
                     <hi>The Ʋnder-Marshal in</hi> Calice <hi>who was a great informer against, and a great Prosecutor of good people, there did suddenly fall down dead and never spake word more says Mr</hi> Fox <hi>in his</hi> Acts <hi>&amp;</hi> Monum.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>IIII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">One angry with an honest Minister for not reading the Common-Prayer under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to do it himself one Lords day and intending to do it again the next Lords day, was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with a dead Palsie, &amp; so hindred of his purpose.</note>OUt of <hi>Leicestershire</hi> it is certified from unquestionable hands, that a Gentleman of good quality and Estate, an Inhabitant in a Parish in that County did very much urge the Minister of the Place to read the Service-Book; when he saw he could not by his importunity prevail with him to do it, out of his extraordinary zeal to propagate that way of Devotion, upon a Lords day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing did himself read it in the Church to the people, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster being a man of a peaceable Spirit did no wayes interrupt him in it, he declared his purpose to do the like again another Lords day following; but on that morning before Church-time, as he was in his Parlour writing a Letter, which according to vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar report somewhat concerned that businesse of the Common-Prayer-Book, he was struck with a dead Palsie on one side which immediately gangrened, so that he became a most loathsome creature, and so stunck that none was able to come near him, in which sad condition he continued roaring and crying out because of his pain, for about three weeks time, and then expired.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>V.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A Minister Baptizing a Child with the sign of the Cross, and at the same time drinking to excess as he rode home that night was kil'd by a fall from his horse.</note>AT the request of an Inhabitant in a Town near <hi>Bilrica</hi> in <hi>Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sex,</hi> a certain conformable Minister that lived not far from thence came over and Baptized his Child, wherein he not onely made use of the Sign of the Crosse, but withall told the people that it was useful to defend from all evil; at the Christning-Feast it seems the Minister (who according to the Apostles rule should have been no Wine-bibber, but an example of Temperance and Sobriety to the rest of the people,) meeting perhaps with that Wine which the French call <hi>Vinum Thrologicum,</hi> which is indeed the best Wine, did at that time drink to excesse, however he would adventure to ride home that night, and going through <hi>Belrica</hi> he could not passe by the Tavern <hi>insalutatam,</hi> but there he calls for a Pint of Wine; the Tintner having at that time more discretion
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152943:32"/>than the Parson, and observing what case he was in, refused to let him have any more Wine, telling him he had drunk too much already, at which the Minister was so enraged, that he immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately took his horse, and as well as he could rode away in a very great chafe towards his Habitation; but as he was going the Vinter being much affected with his Condition, and fearing lest some disaster might befal him in his way, because he saw he was not well able to sit his Horse, did very kindly offer him a Servant of his to wait upon him home, which he with great scorn and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation refused; however the Vintner commanded one pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately to follow him, who after he was gone a little way from <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rica,</hi> seeing him fall from his horse, ran immediately to help him up; But the Parson was exceeding angry with him for following him, and charged him to return home again, and gave him twelve pence to do so, and then he getting up on horseback again, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving rid but a very little way further, fals down again, &amp; the man that followed him went with all the speed he could make to help him, but when he came to him he found him stark dead; The truth of this is notoriously and publiquely known in those parts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How many examples like to this have been known heretofore, and amongst them also some drunken superstitious Priests,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Paralel.</note>
                     <hi>you may see at large,</hi> Clarks Exam. p. 146. <hi>ee also</hi> Divine Traged. p. 19.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>VI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">One reading the Common-Prayer, as it is feared against his light, was strucken sick and died.</note>MAster <hi>Bartholomew</hi> the late Minister of <hi>Camden</hi> in <hi>Glocester<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> who was sometime a zealous stickler for Presbyterian Reformation, and did exceedingly oppose and Preach against the Common-Prayer-Book, was yet prevailed with to read some part of it, as it is feared much against his Light and Principles; But the very first Lords day that he read it, he was strucken with sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and died before the next morning.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel.</note>
                     <hi>The like Judgement happened to one</hi> Cox, <hi>who was a zealous asser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the Truth in King</hi> Edward 6. <hi>his time; But when</hi> Queen Mary <hi>came to the Crown, he embraced the Religion which was then in fashion, and afforded best preferment, it pleased the Lord that he going at night well to bed, died before the morning; see</hi> Beard Theatre, &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 42.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>One</hi> Dan. Basil. <hi>Professor of Divinity at</hi> Prague <hi>in</hi> Bohemia, <hi>a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Apostate, was surprized also with sudden death,</hi> Bohe. Hist. <hi>p.</hi> 358.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>VII.</head>
                  <p>ONe <hi>Thomas Buttler</hi> of <hi>Kingston</hi> upon <hi>Thames</hi> in <hi>Surrey,</hi> who was a bitter enemy to Mr. <hi>Mayo</hi> the Godly able Minister<note place="margin">* A forward man in prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Mr. <hi>Mayo</hi> for not reading the Common-prayer-book, found drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the River of <hi>Thames.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:152943:32"/>of that Town, and was most principally active of any other in preferring a Bill of Indictment against him for not reading the Common-prayer-book, was seen on the 17. of <hi>October</hi> 1660. (which was about a fortnight after the preferring the said Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) to come drunk out of an Alehouse or Tavern in <hi>Kingston,</hi> and for four dayes after he could not be heard of any where, till at the four dayes end he was found drowned in the River of <hi>Thames.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is observable that one</hi> Wright <hi>an Inhabitant of this same Town of</hi> Kingston, <hi>a notorious scoffer at Religion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel.</note>
                     <hi>and a violent persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the reverend Minister of the said Town, the immediate prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessor of the present Incumbent (though he was not drowned) yet was suddenly struck with a dead</hi> Palsie, <hi>and lay in a most miserable condition for a short time and then died; see</hi> Divine Traged. <hi>p.</hi> 22.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <head>VIII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Several men urge a Minister to read Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer &amp; give them the Sacrament, for not doing of which they combine toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to doe him some mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief wherein they were prevented by the suddain cutting off of 7 of them by the stroak of death.</note>MAster <hi>Woodward</hi> Minister of <hi>Dursly</hi> in <hi>Glocestershire,</hi> being very desirous to preserve the Ordinances of Christ from polution and defilement, did in the former times keep back from the Lords Supper some notorious scandalous impenitent persons in his Parish, who upon the late re entry of the Bishops, did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to take courage and come to the Minister, demanding of him to read the Common-prayer-book, and to admit them to the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; Upon his refusal to gratifie their importunity in either of them, they went away very much dissatisfied and enraged, and entered into a Combination the next Sacrament day to press in upon him, when he was administring the ordinance, and if he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused to admit them, that then they would do him some mischief; but it pleased the Lord before that day came, to take away six of those persons by death one after another, &amp; a seventh being struck sick immediately told his wife he should die, though there was then outwardly but very little sign of so sudden a change, but he taking his bed with the conceit of it, intreated his wife to send for Mr. <hi>Woodward</hi> the Minister to come to him, telling her still he was sure he should die of that sickness; according to his desire his wife sent for Mr. <hi>VVoodward,</hi> unto whom when he came to him he did freely unbosome himself, and told him the whole story of the Combination above mentioned, and begged his pardon, together with his prayers to the Lord for him, withall telling him that he knew he should die as the rest of his companions had done before him, and intreated Mr. <hi>VVoodward</hi> to Preach at his Funeral, and then declare unto the people what he had now discovered to him, which accordingly he did.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:152943:33"/>
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man speaking against the Phanaticks, was struck speechless and afterwards <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ed.</note>IT is certified from very good hands concerning one Mr. <hi>Town<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sends</hi> Daughter of the City of <hi>Worcester,</hi> that being present at a Bonefire in <hi>Worcester,</hi> the evening of that day (according to our best Information) when his Majesty was proclained, that she drunk healths, and most violently railed against and bitterly cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed the Phanaticks, it pleased the Lord that the same night her speech was suddenly taken from her, and her tongue very much swelled in her mouth, and within four days after or thereabouts she died; her Father sent to Mr. <hi>More</hi> an eminent Minister in that City, desiring him to bury her with the Book of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prayer, upon his refusal he got one <hi>Horril</hi> who lived not far from thence, a man of a very ill fame to do it, and when he should have read, his eye-sight was utterly taken away from him, he tryed se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Books but could read in none of them, the people waited near a quarter of an hour, till at last another Parson was by the friends of the deceased requested to do that office for them, who (though as it is thought not canonically qualified for the service) in such an exigency did undertake it, but performed it so confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sedly that all present were exceedingly astonished at it! This is a truth attested by several Citizens of note and credit in <hi>Worcester,</hi> and indeed too notorious to be contradicted by any.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>X.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Several Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformists committed to prison, those who were their violent Prosecuters stricken with sicknesse and died.</note>ABout twenty sober Religious people being met together near <hi>Carmarthen</hi> to Worship God, were taken and carried to that Town, as they went through the Streets they were much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bused by railing speeches; and some that were more rude and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous threw stones at them as they peaceably passed along, in which actions there was one Mrs. <hi>Simmons</hi> that was observed to be more forward than all the rest, one Mr. <hi>Bird</hi> also <hi>Tertullus</hi> like, did most vehemently accuse and implead these poor Christians, it was so remarkable that the Justice himself according to the duty of his place, did publiquely check him for being so busie and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in that wherein he was not at all concerned; The Mayor also of the Town was exceeding cruel to them, committing them to the Dungeon for some space of time, they continued about five weeks in Prison, during which time or a few days more, the Mayor and his wise, the aforesaid Mr. <hi>Bird,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Simmons</hi> were by the hand of the Lord smitten with sicknesse and died, to the great admiration both of Town and Country.</p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:152943:33"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We read that in the time of the seventh Persecution under</hi> Decius <hi>the Emperour,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel.</note>
                     <hi>when</hi> Secundianus <hi>and others suffered for the Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of Christ, that those that were most forward and cruel in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting that bloody work, were cut off by sudden death.</hi> Clark Marty. p. 53.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <head>XI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">One who did rayl at, and curse a saith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Minister and other good people was soon after stricken with a dead palsie, and lay curs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing till he died.</note>MAster <hi>Symmes</hi> the Minister of <hi>Wimbleton</hi> in the County of <hi>Surrey,</hi> being by the violence of one of the Church-wardens hindred from preaching in the publick place, did preach at his own dwelling house to as many as were free to come thither to hear him; It was very much observed that one <hi>Nathaniel Pace,</hi> an Inhabitant of that Town of <hi>Wimbleton,</hi> did most bitterly rail against Mr. <hi>Symmes</hi> and the meeting, and was heard often with very great rage and violence to curse them, and to breath out threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning words against them, but this he did more especially on one Lords day, which was <hi>October</hi> the 7. 1660. And it pleased the Righteous and just God, that on the very next day when the said <hi>Nathaniel Pace</hi> was upon the Heath cutting Furses, he was struck with a double Palsie (as it was conceived) but he presently begun to recover and grow better for a few hours, so that he was able to return to his work, but after he had a while continued so, he grew very ill again, and then fell down as dead among the Furses, he was not found till 2 of the Clock at night, and then was carried home where he came to life again, but lay raving, cursing, and swearing till he died, which was within very few days after.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel.</note>
                     <hi>Thus it happened to a violent Hater and Persecutor of a godly Minister in</hi> Hungary, <hi>God struck him with sicknesse and soon after he ravingly died.</hi> Fox, Acts <hi>and</hi> Monum.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>XII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">One who ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciously pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secured an honest man for delivering some Books to his Friend while he was wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ing to a Justice of Peace about it, was struck dead before he could send his letter away.</note>BY a Letter from an unquestionable hand in <hi>Yarmouth</hi> bearing date <hi>January</hi> 28. 1660. We are assured that the Clark of the Peace for the County of <hi>Norfolk,</hi> did most maliciously prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute one Captain <hi>Salter</hi> for giving a Book (which contained a Narrative of the several executions of those ten men who suffered in <hi>October</hi> last) to a Gentleman, a friend of his in that County, Captain <hi>Salter</hi> was bound over to the Sessions, and the Clark of the Peace writes a Letter to one of the Justices who lived near to the Gentleman, to whom Captain <hi>Salter</hi> gave the aforesaid Books, that he should binde him over to appeare at the Sessions to Testifie against the said Captain <hi>Salter,</hi> when he had finished this Letter, on the back-side of it, he writes down several
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:152943:34"/>questions which he defired the Justice to propound to the said Gentleman when he should appear before him, <hi>viz. what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles had been lately kept at his house, and who the persons that met there, &amp; what miracles Captain</hi> Salter <hi>did deliver to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to his knowledge,</hi> when he had done this, before he could come out of his study to send away his Letter, he fell down dead and never came to life again, one coming in to him found this letter just finished, and seeing the contents of it, sent for the Gentleman whom it concerned, and shewed it him, who took a Copy of it, by which means we come to know the certain Truth of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel.</note>
                     <hi>In the year</hi> 1510. <hi>one</hi> Augustine <hi>a Lawyer, a great stickler a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst, and a malicious persecutor of the Nonconformists in</hi> Bohemia <hi>(called then the BROTHERS) was stricken from Heaven with the stroak of sudden death, while he was in his house sitting at supper.</hi> Bohem. Hist. p. 75.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Also Dr.</hi> Duning <hi>Chancellour in the same County of</hi> Norfolk, <hi>a bloody persecutor in Queen</hi> Maries <hi>daies, was suddenly taken sitting in his Chair and died.</hi> Fox Acts <hi>and</hi> Monu. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <head>XIII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Two men who violently prosecuted an honest Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster smitten dead before they came to testifie against him,</note>THere was a malicious person in <hi>Salisbury</hi> whose name was <hi>Payne,</hi> a Brewer, who did inform some of the Justices against Mr. <hi>Troughton</hi> a Godly Minister in that City, the 27 of <hi>November,</hi> 1660. was the day appointed for the Justices to come over to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lisbury</hi> to hear this Information, and examine some witnesses up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it; But it pleased the Lord that the aforesaid <hi>Payne</hi> (who was to be chief witnesse against this good man, and had made a vow not to Brew any more Ale till he had driven him out of the City) died within a very few hours before the time oppointed for hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the businesse, so that the Justices were constrained for want of Testimony to return from <hi>Salisbury re infecta.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Much about the same time another also of the said City whose name was <hi>Hater,</hi> a violent and malicious Prosecutor of the said Mr. <hi>Troughton,</hi> was suddenly taken away by death; of the hand of God against those two men, great observation hath been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, both of the generality of the Citizens and some of the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mr.</hi> Richard Sedgwick <hi>an eminent gracious man, and an able preacher of the Gospel for many years together at</hi> Wapping,<note place="margin">The Parallel.</note>
                     <hi>was in his younger daies called to be the Minister to the Merchant-Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turers Company at</hi> Hamborough, <hi>amongst whom he did very much good, being Instrumental in drawing many souls to Jesus Christ, at
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152943:34"/>which the Divel was very much enraged, and stirred up an eminent Merchant of the Company against him, because of his impartiall dealing in his Ministry, and the order in the Church, (the only crimes wherewith Mr.</hi> Troughton <hi>above mentioned was charged by his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versaries) who threatned that by such a day, and named it, he should be sent away for</hi> England, <hi>and dismissed his employments; but before that day came, the Merchant himself was summoned by death to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place.</hi> Clarks Marty. p. 397.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="section">
                  <head>XIV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A violent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutor of good men strucken dead suddenly at <hi>Kingston.</hi>
                     </note>UPon the first day of the Assizes, being <hi>March</hi> the 4. 1660. at <hi>Kingston,</hi> it pleased the Lord to strike with sudden death as he was drinking a Glasse of Wine in the Castle Tavern there, the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Shriff of that County, a notorious hater and persecutor of Nonconformists, and a most violent stickler for the Common-Prayer-Book, and it is well known that at the time of his death, he was maliciously prosecuting some thing of that nature, against some honest peaceable people in that County.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>One</hi> Mornay <hi>a French man immedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tely after he had been instrumental to bring a godly Protestant to the Stake, was by sudden death taken out of the world.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Parallel.</note> Acts <hi>and</hi> Monuments.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="section">
                  <head>XV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A woman was envious against a godly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster, wishing her fire in his b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lly, which fire burned her ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>se and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers before night.</note>AT <hi>Ilmister</hi> in <hi>Somersetshire,</hi> a woman who very much hated a godly able Minister that was newly turned out of his Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, there as she was bringing home fire which she had fetched from a Neighbours house, wished that it were burning in the said Ministers belly; the same day as it is reported there was acted in the Town a Play in derision (as some do affirm) of that which they call the Rump-Parliament;) This woman made great hast to dispatch her businesse that she might be at leisure to attend the Divertisement of so good an exercise as that Play was, and it seems in her hast did leave her fire (kindled by that which a little before she wished in the Ministers belly) very carelesly,<note place="margin">One that went to a place not far from his own house, in order to the promoting of a mischievous design against some Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formists or his Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn sell down dead from his h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rse.</note> insomuch that her own house with about twenty six houses more, upon or near the Market-place were before night burnt down to the ground.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="section">
                  <head>XVI.</head>
                  <p>A Certain person whose name was <hi>Mason,</hi> an Inhabitant of <hi>Mountgomery</hi> in <hi>VVal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> went one day from the said Town to a Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m, not far distant, in pusuit of a cruel and malicious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign against some Nonconform<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sts in those parts, in his return home between the Farm and the Town he fell from his horse and lay for dead, his horse coming home without him, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152943:35"/>search being made for him, at last he was found and brought to a Neighbours house neer the place where he fell, it was not long before by the use of means he came to life again, but like a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stracted man he continued a few daies and died.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="section">
                  <head>XVII.</head>
                  <p>A Gentleman of good quality, and a very credible person, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a visit to a great Lady not far from <hi>Charing-cross,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A Lady who uttered very horrid blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous words was not long a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ter taken away by death.</note> was entertained by her with very bitter Invectives against the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-party, from whom she had received in former times very great civilities and towards whom during all those times she was exceeding moderate; But now, not like the same woman very much transported with passion against them; The Gentleman en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to calm her spirit, and amongst other discourse told her <hi>it was not good for any to be too confident, for if we provoke God by our wickedness, he could easily as he had done this, so make another change in a moment if it pleased him;</hi> She replied in a very great passion, <hi>No it as impossible for God himself to make another Change;</hi> A very little while after the same Gentleman seeing her husband in <hi>VVestminster-hall</hi> in mourning, asked him the cause of his wearing that mourning habit, he replied to him, that his wife was lately deceased; And we would in charity hope that God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that change passed upon her selfe did convince her of the Truth of that Scripture, <hi>Psal.</hi> 135. <hi>v.</hi> 5, 6. <hi>The Lord is great, and our Lord is above all Gods, whatsoever the Lord pleased, that did he in Heahen and in Earth, in the seas, and in all deep places.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Paralel.</note>
                     <hi>One</hi> Libanir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s <hi>of</hi> Antioch <hi>immediately after his speaking horrid blasphemous words died suddenly, &amp;c.</hi> Clarks Examples, p. 46.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Also one</hi> Dennis Bennifield <hi>for uttering many blasphemous speeches was smitten by the Lord with sudden death as she was going between</hi> London <hi>and</hi> Hackney. Acts <hi>and</hi> Monuments.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">One who thirsted after the blood of other men, suddenly sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards died, and blood is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sued out of him to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note>
                     <hi>VVe could easily collect many more instances of the same kind, but we omit them to avoid prolixity.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="section">
                  <head>XVIII:</head>
                  <p>ONe Mr. <hi>Russell</hi> an Apothecary in <hi>Bucklers-berry</hi> London, being in company with some persons of good quality and credit, amongst other discourse inveighed most bitterly against Phanaticks, and said that more of them must be hanged, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> One of them replied to him, that he hoped that the blood which
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152943:35"/>had been lately spilt at <hi>Charing-crosse</hi> and <hi>Tyburn,</hi> would satisfie him and the rest of his Friends, he answered no, we must have the blood of more of them yet, and so named divers persons who were formerly active for the Parliament, and if they might have the blood of those men he believed then they should be all satisfied, but not till then; It pleased God that this man went home and that night sickned and grew worse and worse, till at last he was desperately ill and full of Torment, and seemed to be extream restless in his Spirit, till at length within a week af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had spoken the aforesaid words, he was taken away by death, and immediately after his breath was out of his body, there issued from his Mouth, Nose, Ears, and Fundament ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great and unusual quantities of blood, to the great admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and astonishment of the beholders, who had not the least knowledge of the above-mentioned discourse, which so imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately preceded his death.</p>
                  <p>Charles <hi>the</hi> 9 <hi>King of</hi> France <hi>whose thirst Could never be quenched with the blood of the Protestants,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Paralel.</note>
                     <hi>by Gods iust judgment fell sick and with great effusion of blood out of many parts of his Body died miserably,</hi> Acts <hi>and</hi> Monuments.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="section">
                  <head>XIX.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">One at a Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire brought his hogtrough to be burnt as the Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks Pulpit, but afterwards his House and barns were bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt by light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</note>AT <hi>Horsney</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> one <hi>Gibbs</hi> a very prophane scoffing man against Religion, did cause his Hogs-trough to be brought forth to a Bone-fire, which was then in the Town, and ordered the wood to be set round it, saying that this was the Phanaticks Pulpit, which he would now have burnt to ashes, and so made himself and the company very merry with that foolish and ridiculous conceit; It pleased the Lord that in a very short time after, this mans House and Barns were set on fire with Lightning from Heaven and all burnt down to the ground, since which time he is observed to be more silent, and forbears his Scoffing invectives against good men.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Paralel.</note>
                     <hi>Immediately after the Q. Mother of</hi> Scotland <hi>had uttered some jearing and scoffing speeches against some distressed Protestants who were slain before the walls of</hi> Leith, <hi>a sudden fire kindled in that Town which burnt up all th Queens Store-houses and Provisions, whereupon she presenty fell sick and died,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A Person re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation to see Major General <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rison</hi> go to his execution, was suddenly taken with a strange Trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulsion fit.</note> Clarks Examp. p. 581.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="section">
                  <head>XX.</head>
                  <p>THe day that Major General <hi>Harrison</hi> suffered <hi>October</hi> 13. 1660. a Pantaloon Ruffainly Gentleman, placed himself near <hi>Newgate</hi> to see the Major General drawn to his Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, one that stood near him observed him often to break forth into most execrable cursing and swearing, he would be frequently wishing, <hi>Oh that the Rogue would come away, that I
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152943:36"/>might see how like a Rogue he looks now he is going to be hanged;</hi> at leng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h <hi>Harrison</hi> came, and as this Gentleman had fixed his eye upon him, he was smitten immediately with such a trembling that he was not able to hold a joynt still, his companions got him into a house that was near, and the person that had obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him curse and swear as before, followed him into the house, and endeavoured to lay the Judgment of God home to his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science, but he seemed sensible of little, but cried out continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, <hi>O I think my heart will come out,</hi> he continued in this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable condition in that House for about the space of two hours, then he was conveyed away by his Friends, and what became of him since we have not heard.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="section">
                  <head>XXI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">One coming o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, rejoycing to a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of his for that Mr. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> was gone to be hanged, a great dog flew upon him and did bite seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall holes in his body to the endanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his life.</note>THe same morning Mr. <hi>Peters</hi> suffered at <hi>Charing-crosse,</hi> which was <hi>October</hi> 16. 1660. A Poulterer in <hi>East-cheap</hi> rejoycing much at the death of that man, came cross the Street to a Butchers shop, rayling most bitterly against Mr. <hi>Peters,</hi> saying to this effect, <hi>Now the Rogue</hi> Peters <hi>was gone to be hanged, and would Preach no more,</hi> &amp;c. While the words were yet in his mouth, a great Dog that lay under the Butchers Stall, came vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently upon him without any provocation at all, bit him and tore him extreamly, and drew him under the Butchera Stall, and could not be gotten off him till he had bitten, as we are informed, 18 or 19 dangerous holes in his body, he was in great hazzard of his life by it, and kept his bed for some weeks after, but as we hear he is since recovered; This Providence was the more remarkable because the Dog was alwayes wont to be very gentle, and never observed either before or since to fly at any one, especially in the day time and in the Street; and besides this Poulterer using daily almost to come over to the Butchers Shop, was as familiar with the Dog, and the Dog with him, as if he had been his Master.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="section">
                  <head>XXII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Two maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous persons who did vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute a good Minister, were suddenly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away by death.</note>ONe Mr. <hi>Anthony Palmer</hi> an able faithful Minister of the Gospel, was by the former Powers setled as Preacher at <hi>Bourton</hi> on the water in <hi>Glocestershire,</hi> where he continued some years, but lately by the force and violence of some few of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants was driven from his Charge, being several times in danger of his life, and so was constrained for a season to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from the place, and did substitute an able Minister to preach in his room; But one of the Parishoners that had been
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:152943:36"/>the chief stickler against Mr. <hi>Palmer,</hi> brings an Episcopal man to read the Common-Prayer-Book there, and one Lords day when he had begun to read, the other Minister whom Mr. <hi>Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> had requested for a time to supply his place for him, went up into the Pulpit and begun to speak to the people what he conceived tended more to their Edification, than what the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was then about, and wherein he so prevailed, that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at last was forced to surcease; Upon this that person be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned (who was so fierce and cruel an enemy to Mr. <hi>Palmer,</hi> and the only considerable Patron in that Parish of this Common-Prayer Book man) stood up in the Congregation, and desired the Neighbours to depart with him, and not to hear such a Phanatique as was in the Pulpit, he prevailed with very few, except his Chaplain to bear him Company; But it pleased the Lord suddenly within a few hours after to strike him with death. Another of the Parish that was his abettor and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the forementioned proceedings, was also suddenly smit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in a very strange manner, his hands grasping one in another that they could not be opened, who in three dayes time was taken out of the world by death also.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Paralel.</note>
                     <hi>One that was Chamberlain to the Emperour</hi> Valens <hi>expressed much discon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent against a Religious Monk because of his frequent preaching, and did at one time, especially in the presence of the Emperour, abuse him with taunts and ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Language, but presently the hand of God stroke him with an Apoplexy and he fell downe dead,</hi> Beard Theat. p. 26.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="section">
                  <head>XXII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">One who was come to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> in order to doe some prejudice to some honest People in his Country was prevented by death.</note>ONe that lived in <hi>Wales,</hi> a great Persecutor of Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mists in his Neighbourhood, being not able to carry on his design against them there, in any proportion to the malice that was in his heart towards them, about Michaelmas last, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to a more severe and effectual prosecution of them, came up to <hi>London,</hi> but his purpose God did wholly frustrate, for wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hin two dayes after his arrival there, he was carried out of the world by death.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="section">
                  <head>XXIV.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">A patron of a living where a godly minister wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> setled having done much injury to this good man, was so over run with lice that he died.</note>ONe Mr. <hi>Constantine</hi> a Minister in <hi>Cheshire,</hi> was most injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sly dealt withal and persecuted by a Gentleman in that County, who was (as we are informed) the Patron of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving where Mr. <hi>Constantine</hi> was setled, but it pleased the Lord to send great swarmes of Lice to this Gentleman, wherewi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h he was grievously infested, and having some convictions upon hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> conscience, he went to Mr. <hi>Constantine,</hi> acknowledged the
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152943:37"/>wrong he had done him, and desired his pardon, and the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of his prayers to the Lord on his behalf; But within a short time he dyed of this noysome disease.</p>
                  <p>Tertullian <hi>writes concerning one</hi> Claudius Herminianus <hi>a great hater and persecutor of the Christians,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The Paralel. Ad Scapulam, p. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>9.</hi>
                     </note>
                     <hi>that God smote him as he did</hi> Herod, <hi>so that he dyed of vermin, but before his death sayes he,</hi> cognito errore suo penè Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus decessit, <hi>being convinced of this error in affl cting the servants of Christ, he died almost perswaded to be a Christian himself.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Maximinian <hi>the Emperour, a cruel Persecutor of the Christians, was by the hand of God struck with a grievous disease, vermin bred abundantly in his body, wherewith he was so infested, that not being able to endure it any longer, he han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged himself,</hi> Euseb.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>One</hi> Phillips <hi>also, a bloody enemy to the Protestants in</hi> Q. Maries <hi>dayes, and particularly to</hi> Mr. Tindal, <hi>a Godly Minister, fell into a grievous sicknesse, and was consumed with Lice,</hi> Acts and Mon.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="section">
                  <head>XXV.</head>
                  <p>UPon the 23 of <hi>March</hi> 1660. a dreadful Judgment was exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by Gods immediate hand upon one <hi>Dorothy Mately</hi> an Inhabitant of <hi>Ashover</hi> in the County of <hi>Derby,</hi> an exact and true relation whereof was taken from the mouth of a very cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible person (who lives in the said Town, and was an eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of this severe stroke) by an eminent Citizen of <hi>London,</hi> who upon occasion hath since that time been at <hi>Ashover,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the information he there received concerning it, did himself draw up the relation following.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Dorothy Mately</hi> lived in <hi>Ashover</hi> in the County of <hi>Derby,</hi> four miles from <hi>Chesterfield,</hi> she was a woman of a very wicked life and conservation, as divers people of the Town informed me, and particularly noted for a common curser, swearer, thief and lyer, and had gotten a constant habit of this Imprecation (in her asserting of any thing,) <hi>I would I might sink into the earth if it be not so, or I would God would make the Earth open and swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me up,</hi> and the like, some of the Town said they had heard her use such like imprecations hundreds of times; Her usual labour that she followed for her living, was to wash the rubbish that came forth of the Lead Groves or Mines, and therein to get sparks of lead ore (as they called them;) And upon the 23 day of <hi>March</hi> 1660. the said <hi>Dorothy</hi> being washing Ore on the top of a steep and Rocky Hill, about a quarter of a mile from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shover,</hi> was taxed for stealing two single pence out of a Youths pocket (who had laid aside his Breeches whilst he wrought in his Drawers) which she violently denied, wishing the ground might swallow her up if she had them, and used the same im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precations several times upon other occasions that day; And
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152943:37"/>one <hi>George Hodgkinson</hi> of <hi>Ashover</hi> a man of good repute amongst his Neighbours, comming accidentally by the place where the said <hi>Dorothy</hi> was at work (the time aforesaid) stood still a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to talk with her, she was washing her Ore in a Tub with a sieve in it, the people shewed me one like to it which I think was near four foot in the Diameter, and about two foot and a half deep; There was a little Girle standing at her Tub side, and another Wench being at some distance called aloud to them and they not understanding what she said, the said <hi>George Hodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinson</hi> went to the Tub side and taking the litle Girle by the hand, said come and go along with me, and hear what the Wench hath to say to you, but as he said he and the Girle were not gone ten yards from the place before he heard the woman behind him crying out for help, and thereupon looking back he saw the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and the Tub twirling round and sinking (as his expressions were) and he, making answer to her cry, said, <hi>pray to God to pardon thy sin, for thou art never like to be seen alive any longer,</hi> or words to this effect, but when the woman and the tub were sunk about three yards down, she stayed a while and called a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain for help, thinking as she said, that she should stay there; and the man being sore amazed, yet beginning to think how to help her, immediately a great stone which appeared in the earth, fell upon her head, and broke her skull, and then the earth fell in upon her, and covered her; She was afterwards digged up, and found about four yards within ground, but her Tub and Sieve was not found, there was found in her pocket the single pence which she had denyed; After conversing with <hi>George Hodgkinson</hi> and some other Inhabitants of <hi>Ashover,</hi> I went to see the place, which is on the top of a Hill as aforesaid, there is a lead Grove or pit about six yards from the place, this grove as the people told me was forty odd Fathom deep cut through hard Rocks, and there was not the least shrinking of earth into that Grove, the place where the woman sunk was a round hole or pit, as I judge about three or four yards deep, and I think about the same breadth at the top, but narrow at the bottom, the ground round about is firm; and not the least crack in it that I could discern, and the very place where the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and her tub stood, appeared the like before her sinking, there lies great weights of stone and Ore all about it, and the like hath done upon that place, I asked the people if they could give any reason for her sinking, and they answered, God only knows the reason (or to that effect) <hi>George Hodgkinson</hi> the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate eye-witnesse, seemed much affected with it, and said he
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:152943:38"/>hoped it would do him good, and that he should have occasion to remember it all the dayes of his life.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="section">
                  <head>XXVI.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">While the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of <hi>Oxford</hi> was conferring orders upon some persons, a ledge of wain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scot fell down upon the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion Table. Also Dr. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Holiday</hi> as he was admin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>string the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament fell down and so wounded him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self that he could not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to officiate any further.</note>ON the 31 of <hi>March</hi> being the Lords day, 1661. two strange accidents happened at Christ-Church in <hi>Oxford,</hi> where the Bishop of the Diocess was met with several of his Clergy to confer holy orders (as they call them) upon several persons, there is some difference in the reports about them.</p>
                  <p>But from a Member of that University, who is a great friend to that way, and will be far from speaking any thing to the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage of that party, take the relation of it as followeth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an extract of a Letter under his own hand, to a person of quality near <hi>London,</hi> dated at <hi>Oxford April</hi> 4. 1661. <hi>in haec ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba,</hi> On Sunday last the Bishop of <hi>Oxford</hi> conferred holy orders at Christ-Church, whilst they were about the Solemnity, two strange and unusal accidents happened, which have already oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casioned discourses here, and I doubt not the story will get with advantage to <hi>London,</hi> the first was that whilst the Bishop was confirming several persons, a great ledge of Wainscote fell down either upon or nigh the Communion table, which it is thought if the Bishop had not been in the body of the Chancel laying hands on the persons to be confirmed, but in the place where he read the prayers it would have done him a mischief; The other accident was that Dr. <hi>Barten Holiday,</hi> the Arch-Deacon of <hi>Oxford</hi> administring the wine at the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (which is alwaies on such occasions to be administred) fell down and hit his face against the chalice, so as to wound himself so much that he was forced to desist and Dr. <hi>Lampluge</hi> of Queens officiated for him.</p>
                  <p>From another member of the same University and as credible a person as the former, we have a more full (yet true) account of this businesse as followeth. Upon the last day of <hi>March</hi> there were many ordained in Christ-Church Chappel, one of which sounded twice that they were forced to intermit till strong wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was fetch'd, after which the Bishop went on in his work, wherein he had not long proceeded before a Canopy made of wainscoat, a great while since erected over the high Alter, fell down upon the late railed Alter &amp; with its fall threw down the bread appointed for the Communion that day, together with the drinking vessels, and made them fly several wayes; but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this a worse thing chanced, when the Table was pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ated again for the Communion, and all consecrated by the Bishop, as Dr. <hi>Holiday</hi> his Lordships Arch-Deacon was marching with
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:152943:38"/>the Cup down the steps from the high Altar to administer it, he fell down with an exceeding violence and cut both his hand and his face, whereby he was utterly dissabled from officiating any further for that time in that service.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="section">
                  <head>XXVII.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Three or four debauched persons In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Worcester</hi> did one the day of his Majesties Coronation drink healths to so great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesse, that two of them fell sick immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately upon it and died.</note>ONe <hi>Luke Hodges</hi> of the City of <hi>Worcester,</hi> with two or three more of his friends and companions, had occasion not long before the 23 of <hi>April</hi> last 1661. (being the day of the Kings Coronation) to ride (according to our best informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) to <hi>Droyt Wych,</hi> where their businesse it seems detained them the day before mentioned, which according to the mode of those that would be accounted the best Subjects, they did celebrate in swearing and rioting, but especially in drinking the Royal healths (though expresly contrary to his Majesties late Proclamation on that behalf;) but these men that they might excell and become paramount in the Solemnity of the day, did agree that the most considerable healths should be honoured with putting alive into every glasse of Wine a little Fish, which in that Country they call a <hi>Loch,</hi> and so to drink down wine and fish together, and if at any time the fish stuck by the way according to their agreement they were to swear and curse it down; when the Solemnity was ended, and they had made use of the ordinary means (sleep) for the recovery of their senses, and were now from beasts in some competent degree transformed into men again, as well as they could rode home to <hi>Worcester,</hi> where the Righteous God immediately calls some of them to an account for their late prophaness and horrible abuse of themselves and his Creatures, and strikes the aforesaid <hi>Luke Hodges</hi> with a desperate and violent sicknesse, during all the time whereof he was in unspeakable torment, and still fancied (as we have credibly been informed) that the Fishes which he drank down did continually gnaw upon him, after a few days sicknesse he miserably ended his life.</p>
                  <p>About the same time another of them whose name was <hi>Segar</hi> the Lord struck much after the same manner, and in a short space of time he also breathed out his last, the rest are for the present reserved to take warning by the example of Gods severe Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon their fellows, whereby the Lord with a very loud and most articul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te voice calls them to a speedy repentance and reformation, <hi>least they likewise perish,</hi> Luke 13.5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The Paralel.</note>
                     <hi>It would fill a considerable Volumne to collect the several judgments that have been inflicted upon Drunkards and Health-drinkers, the Reader may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish himself with variety of Examples of this kind if he look into</hi> Beards I heat. <hi>&amp;c. And</hi> Clarks <hi>Examples, and a book called a Divine Tragedy; we shall only pick out these three short instances, which come the nearest to a Paralel of any that we can find.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:152943:39"/>1. <hi>At the Plough in</hi> Barnwel <hi>near</hi> Camb. 4 <hi>persons were engaged in this sin of drunknesse, and drank so much that within a short time after three of them died &amp; the fourth narrowly escaped after a very great sicknesse,</hi> Clarks Exam. p. 148.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Also at a place near</hi> Mauldon <hi>in</hi> Essex, 4 <hi>or</hi> 5 <hi>persons appointed a drinking match, and did there abuse the Creatures of God to very great excess, they drank Healths in a very st<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ange manner, whereof all of them dyed in a very short time after,</hi> Clark. ibid. p. 149.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>To these two, we shall adde only one more; An Episcopal conformable Minister going down</hi> (Anno 1634.) <hi>on a Saturday night with some of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours into the Country, the next day being the Lords day, they went in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon a little way to visit a</hi> London <hi>Minister, who had another living in the Country, he entertained them very courteously with good store of Sack,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the Parson who was the visitant drank so freely, that he was ill all night, and the next morning grew worse, his Neighbours got him home as well as they could to</hi> London, <hi>and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fore the next Lords d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y following he died,</hi> Divine Trag p. 28.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The Conclusion.</head>
               <p>VVE have now given a faithful account to the world of those great and remarkable providences which have come to our knowledge within the compass of the respective times mentioned in the foregoing Narrative. Many other particulars of the like nature we have by us, which came to our hands to late to accompany these which we have now published. We shall therefore reserve them together with what of the like k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd may for the future from good hands be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to us (wherein we beg the utmost assistance from all the Lords People in the several Countries) to another season,<note n="*" place="margin">this is not that Sermon of <hi>Luthers,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the same Text which was heretofore translated into <hi>English,</hi> and Printed at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, Anno.</hi> 1570 though that also be a Discourse well worthy the Readers most diligent perusal.</note> which if the Lord vouchfase, they shall see the Light also. In the mean while, we cannot but recommend to the Readers most serious perusal, an excellent Discourse of Dr. <hi>Martin Luther</hi> (that Faithful S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rvant of Jesus Christ against Antichrist) upon <hi>Luke 21. vers. 25.26. &amp;c.</hi> being very lately by an able and faithful hand, with great exactness Translated out of his E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arrations on the Gospels and Writings of the Apostles and other places of Scripture, Printed at <hi>Bufil, Anno 1546.</hi> Which Sermon as we judge doth most lively open and apply the foregoing History of the great and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous Works of the Lord, which cannot indeed be rightly known or understood but by his Word. And what this Famons and Eminent Light of the Church did De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and Teach so long agoe, is exact<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y calculated for this year of Prodigies and Wonders. We read in <hi>Rev. 4. vers. 5. That out of the Throne of God, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded Lightnings, and Thundrings, and Voices, &amp;c.</hi> By Lightnings and Thundrings, we may well understand the Terrible and Dreadful Works and Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sations of God, which being alone, make but a very uncertain sound, but <hi>Voic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> (which signifie the Preaching of the Word) being joyned with them, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y may the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re clearly be understood, and the better improved <hi>by all those that take pleasure therein.</hi> Now as Face answers Face in a Glass, so truly and fully doth the foregoing Narrative in all things comport with the forementioned Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, upon which account we do the more affectionately at this time recommend it to the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ber and Judicious Reader, praying unto the Lord, that all those who shall have Hearts and Opp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtunity to look seriously into it, may thereby through D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vine Blessing, be fully instructed in the Mind and Meaning of God, in these late Eminent and Signal Works and Wonders of his Providence amongst us.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152943:39"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152943:40"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152943:40"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>